<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The figure of Antichrist with the tokens of the end of the world, most plainly disciphered by a Catholike and diuine exposition of the seconde epistle of Paul to the Thessalonians, collected out of the best and most approued diuines, both olde and new, very profitable for all men in this age to reade: published by Thomas Tymme, minister.</title>
            <author>Tymme, Thomas, d. 1620.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1586</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 217 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 95 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14107</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24417</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102039</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837840</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837840</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2186</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14107)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2186)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1040:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The figure of Antichrist with the tokens of the end of the world, most plainly disciphered by a Catholike and diuine exposition of the seconde epistle of Paul to the Thessalonians, collected out of the best and most approued diuines, both olde and new, very profitable for all men in this age to reade: published by Thomas Tymme, minister.</title>
                  <author>Tymme, Thomas, d. 1620.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[93] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By T. Dawson] for Fraunces Coldocke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1586.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-M[-M6-8].</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Some pages tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Thessalonians --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2186:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2186:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Figure of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte, with the</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of the end of the world, <hi>moſt plainly diſciphered by a</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike and Diuine expoſition <hi>of the ſeconde Epiſtle of</hi> Paul to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> collected out of the beſt and moſt approued di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, both olde and new, very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for all men in this age to reade:</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by <hi>Thomas Tymme,</hi> Miniſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jmprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> for <hi>Fraunces Coldocke.</hi> 1586.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_names">
            <pb facs="tcp:2186:2"/>
            <head>The names of the authors, out of whoſe workes this expoſition is taken, are theſe following.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Bullinger.</item>
               <item>Caluin.</item>
               <item>Pelican.</item>
               <item>Paraphraſt.</item>
               <item>Orcamenius.</item>
               <item>Pomeranus.</item>
               <item>Eraſmus Sarcerius.</item>
               <item>Iodochus Willichius.</item>
               <item>Vitus Theodorus.</item>
               <item>Chriſtoph. Hofman.</item>
               <item>Aug. Marlorat</item>
               <item>Chitraeus.</item>
               <item>Muſculus.</item>
               <item>Irenaeus.</item>
               <item>Tertullian.</item>
               <item>Auguſtine.</item>
               <item>Chriſoſtom.</item>
               <item>Ambroſe.</item>
               <item>Theophilact.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2186:2"/>
            <head>¶To the Right <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful Sir Robert</hi> Wing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feeld Knight, Thomas Tymme <hi>wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth increaſe of worſhip, with all ſpiritual</hi> grace and benediction in this life, and perfit felicitie with the ſaintes, in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, in the life to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Euangeliſt,<note place="margin">Luke. 1. Acts. 1.</note> S. Luke (Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull) had his <hi>Theophilus</hi> to whom hee dedicated his Goſpell: a diuine matter, to a godly ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This example may ſeeme to haue procured many good men ſince that time, to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the fruite of their learned ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, to ſome of godly qualitie, that they might be as a Rampier to their vertues, to repell thoſe whelpes of <hi>Cerberus</hi> that helliſh dogge and a bar to peeuiſh <hi>Momus,</hi> which will euer be finding fault in <hi>Apelles</hi> woork. Seeing therfore that many of the beſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:2186:3"/> fathers in theſe latter euill times, haue gladly ſought the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of great ſtates, I thought it not good to publiſhe this little booke, without the countenance of ſuch a one as might be a patrone to the ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e againſt ſuch peuiſh carpers. The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it ſelfe is ſuch, as it needeth not the weake defence of man, being the doctrine of the holy Ghoſt, vttered by the bleſſed mouth of S. Paul: and yet the children of God, are bound to defend and aduaunce it to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt of their power, on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the Lorde Chriſt, (to ſhew their zeale and loue) againſt his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie, that monſter Antichriſt: for the vnderpropping of whoſe king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, thoſe kings and nations of the earth,<note place="margin">Apoc. 17.2. and 18.3.</note> which haue taſted of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunted cup of fornication of the <hi>Babilonicall</hi> Strumpet, (which is a more peſtilent cup then that <hi>Nectar</hi> of <hi>Cyrces,</hi> which transformed men into beaſtes) do band themſelues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether euen at this day, and thereto do bend their whole forces. But the Lorde will ſhortly deſtroye that man
<pb facs="tcp:2186:3"/> of ſin with the breath of his mouth.<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 1.</note> This is the matter (Right Woorſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) in it ſelfe excellent, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon knowledge whereof is very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, becauſe it occaſioneth a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the end of the world therunto annexed, to awake careleſſe <hi>Atheistes,</hi> which are lulled aſleepe with worldly pleaſure in the cradle of ſecuritie: The expounders alſo of the Apoſtle Paules minde in this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, (whoſe names are hereto prefixed) are ſuch principall pillars of the chriſtian Church, as their iudg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment will ſtand firme with out any iuſt controlement. My paines in the collection and tranſlation out of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine into Engliſhe, (the leaſt, yet faithfully herein beſtowed) I offer to your woorſhippe, crauing accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of ſo ſmall a gift. And becauſe my caſe may paraduenture nowe ſtand no better then it did longe ſince with the Philoſopher <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odorus Athenienſis,</hi> who complayned of great diſcourteſie ſhewed vnto him, becauſe thoſe thinges which he gaue with the right hande, were
<pb facs="tcp:2186:4"/> ſnatched vp and taken by his audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie with the left: meaning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his workes and lectures which he publiſhing to good purpoſe, were wreſted and ſunderly by captious carpers canuaſſed with ſiniſter inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations: therfore in moſt dutifull humility, I ſhroud my ſelfe vnder the cloake of your courteſie, which I heare and partly knowe to be ſuch, as I looke not to bee ſhouldred out and reiected, but freely to be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the benefite of your goodnes. In aſſured hope whereof, I reſt, leauing this as a teſtimonye to the worlde, what a reuerend opinion I haue of you, both in reſpect of your humble courteſie, (wherein you ſhew foorth the right patterne of a Gentleman) &amp; alſo in reſpect of that godly zeale toward the Goſpell of Chriſt, which by effect hath alwayes appeared to be in you. Thus praying God to bleſſe your worſhippe, I wiſh charitie from God to the world, peace at length to his warfaring Church, confuſion of all manner of hypocrits, fauourable
<pb facs="tcp:2186:4"/> inclination and Iudgment of great perſonages to his worde, and to the godly trauellers in his Goſpell long life, and moſt proſperous reigne to our gratious ſoueraigne Prince, and true happines to al her ſubiects that wiſh the ſame: And euen with my whole hart, I pray God the father of heauen, and his ſonne our Lord Ieſus Chriſte, to be a bright pillar to vs in the darkneſſe of this worlde, and to make all his choſen people at his time, partners of the moſt ioyful and heauenly kingdome. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips euer to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded <hi>Thomas Tymme.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:2186:5"/>
            <head>The Argument.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>ECAVSE the Apoſtle Paul could not conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly returne any more to ſee the <hi>Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> he confirmeth their mindes by this Epiſtle, that they might conſtantly beare and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure affliction for Chriſtes ſake, for the which they ſhold receiue their reward, and their aduerſaries alſo their iuſt Iudgment from the Lorde. This is the content of the firſt chapter. Furthermore, becauſe he had written vnto them in the former Epiſtle, that the laſt day woulde come vnawares, and had for the ſame cauſe alſo admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed them to watch, &amp; not to be careleſſe: the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> thought that they ſhould liue to ſee the laſt day. Wherfore in the ſeconde chapter, hee doth confute that vaine and falſe opinion, concerning the comming of Chriſt at hand (which with moſt men at that time had preuayled) by the argument, becauſe firſt there muſt be a departing awaye in the church, and a great parte of the worlde muſt fall from God: and Antichriſt muſt reigne in the
<pb facs="tcp:2186:5"/> Temple of God: vpon the which ſonne of perdition, the Lorde Ieſus will at the laſt take vengeance, and wil alſo kil him with the breath of his mouth. The comming &amp; kingdom of which Antichriſt, the Apoſtle doth plainly diſcipher, that the latter age being forewarned therof, might take heed of the peſtilent cup of that <hi>Babilonicall</hi> purple coloured ſtrumpette. In the thirde chapter, after that hee hath commended himſelfe vnto their prayers, &amp; hath bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly incouraged them to conſtancie, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth that thoſe men be ſeuerely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed which through idlenes and curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie troubled the common wealth: vvhom he vvould haue to be excommunicated, if ſo be they vvould not bee admoniſhed and vvarned. Finally, he finiſheth his Epiſtle by recommending them to the Lorde of peace. The vvhich Epiſtle although it be breefe, yet a contayneth vvoonderful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and learning. In ſtyle it is nothing dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the former Epiſtle, neither in any thing inferior. That it vvas ſent from Rome (as commonly the Greek books reporte) it is not like: for had it beene ſo, he vvould haue made ſome mention of his
<pb facs="tcp:2186:6"/> bondes, according to his vvoonted man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Furthermore, he ſhevveth that hee is in preſent perill of vnreaſonable and euill men. Whereof it may be gathered, that he did write this Epiſtle as hee vvas in his iourney tovvarde <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> And the Latines haue a long time beene of opinion that it vvas vvritte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from <hi>Athens.</hi> Some alſo thinke that it vvas ſent by <hi>Titus</hi> &amp; <hi>Oneſimus.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:2186:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>CHAPTER. I.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="1">1 Paul, and Siluanus, and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motheus vnto the Church of the Theſſalonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in God our father, and in the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Grace bee with you, and peace from God our father, and from the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>PAVL and Silua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, and Timothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi> As in the former Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians,</hi> ſo in this Epiſtle alſo the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle beginneth, retayninge the ſame forme of ſubſcription, title, and ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Apoſtle Paule himſelfe being the author of this Epiſtle, doth neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe vouchſafe, to make others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſortes with him of the ſame, which were his woorkefellowes in the miniſterie of the worde, not arrogating to him ſelfe alone the prerogatiue and prehemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (as thoſe doe which ſeeke themſelues) but ſhewing his common conſent with others in doctrine, which were the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants
<pb facs="tcp:2186:7"/> of Chriſt; he ioyneth two with him as authors of the Epiſtle. <hi>Siluanus</hi> was a diligent helper of Paul in the Goſpel, who preached Chriſt to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> as appeareth in the ſame E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle where it is ſaide, <hi>For the ſonne of God Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.19. Act. 15.22.</note> 
               <hi>who was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched among you by vs, that is, by me and Siluanus, and Tymotheus, &amp;c.</hi> This <hi>Siluanus,</hi> is euen the very ſame which in the Acts of the Apoſtles is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Silas,</hi> (as ſome coniecture) the name being ſomewhat enlarged and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med according to the manner of the Grekes and Latines. <hi>Tymotheus,</hi> was the ſonne of a certaine godly and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full woman of <hi>Iudea,</hi> whom the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle calleth <hi>Eunice:</hi> but his father was a Greke,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.5.</note> and his graundmothers name was <hi>Lois.</hi> This man preached Chriſt at <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> and kept Paul company going into <hi>Aſia.</hi> Thus then we ſee, that the Apoſtle writeth his Epiſtle in the name of three, both to ſhewe that they did all agree together in teaching, and alſo to bring the more authoritie and credit vnto his Epiſtle. For there is
<pb facs="tcp:2186:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> more credit giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to many of one profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and miſterie, than to one alone: according to the common prouerb, No man is ſo quicke ſighted, that he can ſee all thinges perfitly. Wherefore Paul very prudently hath inſerted the names of his conſortes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vnto the Church of the Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians in God our Father.</hi> By theſe woords he declareth y the true Church was among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> and they doe contayne, a notable deſcription of the Church which is the true and lawfull ſpouſe of Chriſt, which among other notes, may be known by this one, namely,<note place="margin">A ſpecial note of the true Church.</note> if it be a congregation gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together in God the father, and in our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt. For there is a Church gathered together in God our father, &amp; in the Lord Ieſus Chriſt: and there is a Church gathered together in the Diuell; as is the malignaunt Church. This title then doth teſtifie, that this Epiſtle was in the firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dedicated to that Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which in <hi>Theſſalonica</hi> agreeing in the vnitie of faith, woorſhipped one God the father,
<pb facs="tcp:2186:8"/> and the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and which ſtedfaſtly beleeued the promiſes of the Goſpell, that in them alone is contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the doctrine of Chriſtian righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and of eternall life. For without the knowledge of them, and faith, no man can bee truely reckoned to apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to the Church of God the father, and of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. And now let vs thinke that this Epiſtle doth no leſſe appertayne to euery one of vs, then it did to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> which are alſo endued with a true and liuely faith in God the father, and in our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: yea rather it doth moſt eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially profite y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church at this day, that it may ſerue as a caueat in theſe latter times, wherein <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is reuealed, to make vs beware of deceiuers: who, without this Epiſtle, could not ſo well be knowne, <hi>Antichriſt</hi> with them ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging in the Church, and ſpoyling the ſame. It is alſo to be noted, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle hath ioyned God the father, and our Lord Ieſus Chriſt together, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ſhewe, that the ſonne is nothing inferior to the father in this matter.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2186:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Grace be with you and peace from God our father &amp;c.</hi> Firſt of al, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle wiſheth vnto them grace, that is to ſay, reconciliation and the endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the holy Gh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t, for there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more to bee deſired, then to haue God our mercifull father: then he wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth vnto them peace, that is, all other good giftes, which are needful for them. For this worde, peace, ſignifieth gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, al ioyful and proſperous ſucceſſe. Therefore what ioy and proſperitie ſoeuer we haue, if we haue not the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God withall, our bleſſing ſhall ſoone be turned into a curſe. So that the onely foundation of our felicitie, is the fauour and loue of God, whereof it commeth to paſſe, that our proſperitie is firme and permanent, and our ſaluation moſt ſure, in the middeſt of aduerſitie. He addeth, that this grace and peace doth come from God the father, to giue vs to vnderſtand, that whatſoeuer good thing commeth to vs, the ſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth from the free grace, goodnes, and fauour of God. He putteth downe the name of <hi>Father,</hi> and not of a Iudge, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="tcp:2186:9"/> we might haue the feeling of his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable loue toward vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And from the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> He ioyneth God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father &amp; the Lord Ieſus Chriſt together, to teach vs, y grace &amp; al other good things are giuen vnto vs for his ſonnes ſake our mediator. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that wee may knowe howe wee ſhalbe ſure to receiue them, namely, if we aſke them for his ſonnes ſake. Thirdly, he giueth vs to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that the ſonne is by nature God, reigning in equall power with the father, and help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs by his diuine power. Therefore he intending to wiſh the ſumme of feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie to the Godly, commeth to the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it ſelf, that is, to the grace of God: the which alone, doth not onely bringe vnto vs euerlaſting bleſſednes, but alſo is the cauſe of all good thinges in this life.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3 We ought to thanke God alwaies for you, brethren, as it is meete, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that your faith groweth exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, and the loue of euery one of you toward another aboundeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt part of the Epiſtle is gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulatorie,
<pb facs="tcp:2186:9"/> and conſiſteth of thanks giuing: for thankes are giuen vnto God, as the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and confirmer of thoſe benefites. After this manner the Apoſtle for the moſt part beginneth all his Epiſtles, giuing thanks with them, vpon whom the gift of Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication is beſtowed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alwaies.</hi> He meaneth that he hath daily new occaſion miniſtred to him of giuing thankes vnto God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For you brethren.</hi> That is to ſay, on your behalfe, for your conſtancie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in ſpirituall thinges, putting the perſons for the things, as we ſhal ſee here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As it is meet.</hi> In theſe woords Paul ſheweth that we are bound to giue thanks vnto God, not onely when he doth power on vs good thinges, but alſo when we call to mind his benefits beſtowed on our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. For wherſoeuer we do ſee the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God to ſhine, we are bound to giue thankes for the ſame. Furthermore the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing health of our brethren ought to be ſo deare vnto vs, that whatſoeuer is giuen vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we ought to take it as beſtowed on our ſelues. Moreouer, if we do conſider
<pb facs="tcp:2186:10"/> the holy vnitie of the body of Chriſt, ſuch mutuall communion and fellowſhip ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be among vs, that we will reckon the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of one member, to be the benefite &amp; gaine of the whole Church. Therefore in prayſing the benefites of God we muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes haue reſpect vnto the vniuerſalitie of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Becauſe that your faith groweth ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cedingly.</hi> Here are repeated the principa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pointes of our religion, as faith, charitie, and ſufferance; but not without cauſe. For becauſe in the former Epiſtle, he had pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the faith and charitie of the <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> now he ſpeaketh of the increaſe of them both. And in very deede it is conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for all the godly to obſerue this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that they daily make a triall and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of themſelues, how much they haue profited. This therefore is the true prayſe of the faithfull, if they grow and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe dayly more and more in faith and in charitie. Moreouer, firſt he gaue thankes vnto God for them: now, he ſaith there is cauſe why he ſhould againe giue thankes for their dayly profiting. And when he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth thankes vnto God for their profiting,
<pb facs="tcp:2186:10"/> he doth thereby ſignifie and declare that as well the increaſe, as the beginning of faith and loue, commeth from God. For if theſe ſprang from the vertue that is in men, the giuing of thankes ſhould be fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or els for nothing.<note place="margin">Three cauſes of thanks gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</note> There are therfore three cauſes of thankes giuing: of the which the firſt is, the increaſe of faith. For faith in ſuch as are conſecrated vnto God, how true and perfect ſoeuer it be, doth not ſodenly come to her full perfection: euen as yong Trees doe not by and by grow to their full bignes: but doe firſt ſpring, then ſhout vp in talneſſe, and at the laſt come to a full groth of a Tree. Euen ſo faith hath her degrees, and is not at the firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fully perfected, but ſeeketh and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to increaſe it ſelfe daily more and more. And that is the meaning of this place of Paul,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.17.</note> where he ſaith <hi>From faith to faith:</hi> that is to ſay, that the ſame in the firſt beginning do not decay, but rather y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it be confirmed more and more, vntil it come to iuſt perfection. For according to our common ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of ſpeaking,<note place="margin">Faith of two ſortes</note> there are two ſortes of faith: one imperfect the which being once begunne, goeth forward
<pb facs="tcp:2186:11"/> by degrees, and increaſeth, and continueth not alway in weaknes: the other is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, the which being many wayes confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, doth conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly reſt it ſelfe on the ſure knowledge and will of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the loue of euery one of you to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward another aboundeth.</hi> The Second cauſe of thankes giuing, is the mutuall loue of the Godly, which bindeth vnto her euery one, whom ſhe findeth in affliction by many benefittes. And although accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the common vſe of the ſacred ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, he is our neighbour which is ioyned to vs by any maner of way, either of dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling nere vnto vs, either of kinred, or of frendſhip, or of ſocietie, or elſe of cuſtome: yet notwithſtanding he alſo ſhalbe our neighbour which ſtandeth in need of our helpe whatſoeuer, although he be not a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen with vs, a fellow, a coſin or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way ioyned vnto vs:<note place="margin">Luk. 10.30.</note> euen as that man was which fell into the hands of theeues. But this loue differeth from that which we owe vnto God,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.10.</note> which loueth him in the higheſt degre which loued vs firſt. This loue is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pietie and worſhip which we owe vnto God. And as the duties of this loue
<pb facs="tcp:2186:11"/> are gathered out of the firſt table, ſo the duties of the other are taken out of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond table: the which loue in that it ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth from the loue of God as from the fountain, it cannot be but very acceptable vnto God. Whereupon it commeth to paſſe that God doth ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times more vrge and require the loue of our neighbour then the loue of himſelfe. For, as it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by the Prophet, he doth preferre the defence, and helpe of the widowes, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe, and the oppreſſed, before the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices offered vnto him.<note place="margin">Eſay. 1.17. Loue is the handmaid of faith. Gal. 5.6.</note> For this loue is the handmaid of faith, and doth ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily wait vpon her, as doth the ſhadow on the body. Becauſe faith, which is auail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able before God, is effectual and working through loue.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4 So that we our ſelues reioyce of you in the Churches of God, becauſe of your patience and faith in all your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, and tribulations that ye ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer.</hi> The Apoſtle could not giue vnto them a greater prayſe, then when he ſayth that he propoundeth them as examples before other Churches to be followed: for that is the meaning of theſe woordes: <hi>We our
<pb facs="tcp:2186:12"/> ſelues reioyce of you in the Churches of God.</hi> And yet Paul doth not ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly boaſt of the faith of the <hi>Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> but ſetteth them foorth as a prouoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to make others the more earneſt to imitate them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Churches of God.</hi> In that he calleth them not his Churches, but the Churches of God, it declareth his humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie &amp; faithfulneſſe. For they are falſe and vntruſtie, who, whenas they ought to be the ſeruants of God and the miniſters of Churches, deſire to be called Lordes, and doe vſurpe authoritie ouer other mens ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Becauſe of your patience.</hi> The third and laſt cauſe of giuing thanks is their patience. But the Apoſtle ſaith not that he doth reioyce becauſe of the faith and loue of the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> but, of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and faith. Wherupon it followeth that patience is the fruite and teſtimony of faith. Therefore theſe woordes ought to be reſolued thus, we reioyce of the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which commeth of faith and doth te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith excelleth in you. Otherwiſe the text ſhould not agree. And in very deed
<pb facs="tcp:2186:12"/> there is nothing that doth hold vs vp more in tribulations then doth faith: the which doth hereby euidently enough appeare, becauſe ſo ſoone as we forget the promiſes of God we fal flat to the ground. Therfore the more that a man doth grow in faith, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more he is armed through pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſtoutly to indure all things: euen as on the contrarie part, cowardice, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in aduerſitie doth bewray our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie: eſpecially at ſuch time as we are to ſuffer perſecution for the Goſpell, the force of faith will ſhew it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Therefore that reioycing of the Apoſtle Paul, was no proud, or vaine boaſting, but godly piety, by which he did exalt and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce with condigne prayſes the fruit of Gods worde, and alſo did reioyce ouer the <hi>Theſſalonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> themſelues, that they were in ſuch wiſe and ſo greatly confirmed, that by no manner of perils or perſecutions, they could be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to forſake the faith. And what was this elſe, but to giue the praiſe vnto God for al this grace &amp; vertue. This place teacheth that the ſaints are layed open to perſecutions and are alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed perpetually in afflictions. For ſo
<pb facs="tcp:2186:13"/> many as will liue godly in Chriſt Ieſus ſhall ſuffer perſecution.<note place="margin">2 Tit. 3.12.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5 Which is a token of the righteous Iudgment of God, that ye may be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted woorthy of the kingdome of God: for the which ye alſo ſuffer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſimple and true meaning of theſe woordes is, that the iniuries and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which the children of God doe ſuffer at the hands of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked and reprobate, do ſhewe foorth as in a glaſſe, that God ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be one day the iudge of the worlde. And this ſentence hath in it a figure called <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtrophon,</hi> or Conuerſion, by which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed the prophane opinion which men do commonly hold, ſo often as the good are afflicted, and the euil are in good caſe. For then we thinke that the world is gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by fortune, and not by God. Hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it commeth that impietie and contempt doe poſſeſſe the heartes of men, as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith in the booke of the Preacher, <hi>Chap. 9. ver. 2.3.</hi> For they which ſuffer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing vnworthily, or without deſerte, do either murmure and accuſe God, or elſe they doe thinke that he hath no care of the actions of men: as the Prophet Dauid
<pb facs="tcp:2186:13"/> ſaith in the Pſalme <hi>73.</hi> Reade the whole Pſalme.</p>
            <p>Contrariwiſe the wicked ware more proude of their proſperitie, as if ſo be there were no puniſhment remayning for them: euen as <hi>Dyoniſius</hi> in his proſperous na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uigation, boaſted that the gods were fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fauourable vnto ſuch as were giltie of ſacrilege. Furthermore, when we doe ſee that the crueltie of the wicked againſt the innocent is not reſtrayned, and that they eſcape without puniſhement, fleſh and blood perſwadeth it ſelfe by and by, that there is no iudgment of God, no puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of wickedneſſe, nor any reward of righteouſneſſe. But Paul on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie part pronounceth, that when God doth ſo ſpare the wicked for a time, and doth wincke at the iniuries which his children ſuffer, iudgment to come is ſet before our eies, as it were in a glaſſe. For he taketh this as a clere caſe, that it cannot be, but that God as he is a iuſt iudge, will one day giue reſt vnto the miſerable, which are now vniuſtlie vexed, and will alſo giue vnto the oppreſſors of the godly their iuſt rewarde. And herevnto tendeth this ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:2186:14"/> of <hi>Peter: If any man ſuffer as a Chriſtian, let him not be aſhamed: but let him glorifie God on this behalfe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>For the time is come that iudgment muſt begin at the houſe of God: if it firſt begin at vs, what ſhall the end be of them which obey not the Goſpell of God? And if the righteous ſcarcely be ſaued, where ſhall the vngodly and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner appeare? Wherefore, let them that ſuffer according to the will of God, commit their ſoules to him in well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as vnto a faithfull creator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore the iudgment of God is called righteous in this place, becauſe it ſhalbe executed vpon thoſe which haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the ſame by their wicked perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and alſo becauſe God ſhal exerciſe the ſame not onely according to the externall, but alſo according to the internall things. A place ſurely very notable: becauſe it teacheth how our mindes are to be ſtirred vp from al the impedimentes of the world ſo often as we ſuffer any manner of aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, namely by calling to minde the iuſt iudgment of God, the which will lift vp our mindes from this world to a higher
<pb facs="tcp:2186:14"/> conſideration. Thus death ſhalbe vnto vs the image of life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That ye may be counted woorthy of the kingdome of God.</hi> The ordinance of God is, that no man ſhalbe woorthy of the kingdome of God without the croſſe. Whereupon Chriſt ſaith, <hi>If any man wil follow me, let him deny him ſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 16.24.</note> 
               <hi>and take vp his croſſe, and follow me.</hi> Now, if any man will goe about to proue by the authoritie of this place, that ſaluation is due by deſert vnto our afflictions, and not to the pasſion and blood of the Lorde, let him way and conſider that place onely which the ſame Apoſtle ſetteth downe to the <hi>Romans,</hi> where he proueth that we are iuſtified by the benefite of faith,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.28.</note> and not by the merit of workes. And in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place he ſaith: <hi>I count that the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of this preſent time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note> 
               <hi>are not woorthy of the glory which ſhalbe ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vnto vs.</hi> Therefore we muſt aſcribe it to the liberalitie and fatherly benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of God, that eternall life is ſaid to be giuen vnto vs of right, and that we are made woorthy of the kingdome of God through afflictions, when as it is moſt
<pb facs="tcp:2186:15"/> cleere that all our habilitie and pliant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to any manner of goodnſſe commeth of God, by whoſe grace we are ſanctified and bleſſed. Moreouer the Apoſtle Paul doth not diſpute here of the cauſe of woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyneſſe: but onely taketh the common doctrine of Scripture, that God doth abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh thoſe thinges in vs which belong to the worlde, that hee may frame and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect in vs a better life: Furthermore that he ſheweth vnto vs through afflictions, the pryce of eternall life. Finally, he doth ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply ſet downe the meane by which the faithfull are as it were hammered and wrought vpon Gods anuile: becauſe by afflictions they are taught to renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the world, and to aſpire to the heauenly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God. Beſide this, they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed &amp; ſtrengthned in the hope of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, when they fight for the ſame. Wherupon he addeth, <hi>For the which ye alſo ſuffer:</hi> Namely vnder the aſſured hope of the promiſe made, which bringeth to paſſe that we doe obtaine the kingdome of God. For ſo Chriſt himſelfe ſpeaketh: <hi>Reioyce and be glad,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>for behold plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful is your reward which is in heauen.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2186:15"/> And the Apoſtle:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.17.</note> 
               <hi>If we ſuffer together with him, we ſhal alſo be glorified with him.</hi> And although no manner of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of them ſelues doe make vs worthy of of the reward and glorie of eternal life, yet neuertheleſſe to denie Chriſt for feare of preſent perils, is a ſinne deſeruing to be puniſhed with eternall death. For as we doe beleeue with the hearte to righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.10.</note> ſo we doe confeſſe with the mouth to ſaluation.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6 For it is a righteous thing with God, to reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence tribulation to them that trouble you.</hi> In theſe wordes the Apoſtle ſheweth how the tribulation of the ſaintes may be vnto them an inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the iuſt iudgement of God.</p>
            <p>For God is an Indifferent iudge counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyſing in equal ballances the inequalitie of both parties, as here, the afflicted, and the afflicting. And what can be more iuſt, then that they which in this world do op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the good and godly, and doe make them liue in exile and baniſhment by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, ſhould ſuffer the ſame thinges themſelues in time to come, which they do to others: and that they ſhould be in reſt
<pb facs="tcp:2186:16"/> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other ſaints, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming out of great tribulation, ſhal receiue an eternal king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom? Thus the Apoſtle toucheth the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of god againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reprobate, to teach them that the faithfull doe reſt in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of the iudgment to come: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God doth not as yet take vengeance on the euil, who notwithſtanding muſt needes ſuffer the puniſhment of their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. Withall notwithſtanding the faithfull doe vnderſtand, that there is no cauſe why they ſhould enuy the momenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and tranſitory felicitie of the wicked, which ſoone after ſhalbe changed &amp; turned into horrible and moſt fearful diſtruction.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7 And to you which are troubled, reſt with vs, when the Lorde Ieſus ſhal ſhew himſelfe from heauen with his mightie angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As it is agreeing with the iuſtice of God, to repay vnto wicked and vngodly men condigne puniſhments, ſo alſo it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with the ſame Iuſtice, to giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to godly and righteous men the reſt and conſolation of eternal life. Great therfore ſhalbe the miſerie and vnhappines of al the wicked, and moſt excellent ſhalbe the feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ie
<pb facs="tcp:2186:16"/> and bleſſednes of the godly. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſtle hath oppoſed reſt againſt the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f tribulation, in the which the godly are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xerciſed in this world without intermiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhal depart from this life, all labour and ſorrow ſhal ceaſe, and reſt &amp; ioy ſhall follow in ſteed thereof.<note place="margin">Apoc. 21.4</note> For God ſhall wipe away al teares from the eyes of his ſaints. This then agreeth with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of <hi>Peter,</hi> where he calleth the day of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt iudgment, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day of reſt. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in this declaration of the good and of the euil, the purpoſe of the Apoſtle was to expreſſe more plainly how prepoſterous &amp; vniuſt the gouerment of the world ſhould be, if God did not defer the puniſhments &amp; rewards vntil another iudgment. Hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to alſo tendeth that which was ſaid vnto <hi>Diues:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 16.25.</note> 
               <hi>Sonne remember that thou in thy life paſt enioyedſt thy pleaſure, but contrariwiſe Lazarus enioyed paine: but now is he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted, and thou art tormented.</hi> The Apoſtle addeth:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With vs.</hi> That he might bring the more credit to his doctrine by the ſence &amp; feeling of his owne faith. For he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that he doth not ſpeake of vnknowne
<pb facs="tcp:2186:17"/> things, when as he placeth him ſelfe with them in the ſame cauſe and condition. And we knowe that they doe deſerue to be beſt regarded, which are exerciſed by longe practiſe in thoſe things which they teach, and doe require nothing of others, but that they be ready to proue and try. Therefore the Apoſtle doth not commaund the <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians</hi> to fight as it were in a ſhadow: but fighting valiantly him ſelfe, he exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them to the ſame warre and fight.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When the Lorde Ieſus ſhall ſhewe him ſelfe.</hi> This is a figure called <hi>Occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patio</hi> or preuention, which the Apoſtle v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> might not be carefull concerning the time wherein the wicked perſecutors ſhalbe afflicted with puniſhments, and the godly which are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted ſhall receiue reſt. The time ſhalbe the comming of Chriſt to iudgment, or the time of iudgment. For the Lord ſhall come a iudge: but from whence?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From Heauen.</hi> That is to ſay, from the habitacle of God, which is perpetuall, wherein is the glorie of the inuiſible God, and the light whereunto no man can at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, ſeeing it is a ſpirituall firmament,
<pb facs="tcp:2186:17"/> in the which dwelleth ſempeternall righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. From thence therefore doe we look for our Lord &amp; ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>who ſhall chang our vile bodie that it may be like to his moſt glorious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philip. 3.21.</note> But this Iudgment ſhal not be before the conſummatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al things. For, til that conſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mation be, the Lord Ieſus ſhall not be reuealed from heauen, as appeareth by many teſtimonies of Scriptures. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe one ſhall iudge all, it muſt needes be in that laſt iudgment which ſhalbe in the end of the world, where he ſhall repay to euery one according to his deedes. Chriſt therfore will ſhut vp and reſerue the times of this preſent world, againſt the time of his iudgment in the latter day. But when this iudgment ſhalbe, it is vncertaine. Wherfore the Lord Ieſus himſelfe doth teſtifie, that the moments of times of this iudgement, and of the glorie of Chriſt to come, ought not to be curiouſly ſearched for, neither yet that they can be knowne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand.<note place="margin">Act. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>It is not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for you to know the times and ſeaſons which the father hath reſerued to himſelfe.</hi> And in another place,<note place="margin">Mar. 13.32.</note> 
               <hi>Concerning that day
<pb facs="tcp:2186:18"/> and houre knoweth no man, neither the Angels which are in heauen, nor the Sonne, but the father onely.</hi> And the Apoſtle ſaith:<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.2. 2. Pet. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>That the day of the Lord ſhall come as a theefe in the night.</hi> And yet for all this ſome fooliſh men haue gone about of late time to prognoſticate, of this day, yea and almoſt of the very houre of the day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With his mightie Angels.</hi> Theſe words do deſcribe and ſet foorth the forme and manner of the comming of Chriſt to iudgment: As if he ſhould ſay, the moſt righteous iudge ſhall not now any more come from heauen in humilitie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, as he did at his firſt comming in our fleſh, but inuironed with an Angelical bande. For it is written: <hi>Thouſand thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands miniſtred vnto him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 7.10.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds ſtood before him.</hi> As ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a puiſant and mightie King hauing a huge hoaſt of picte and choſen men, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth forward againſt his enimie, euen ſo the Lord Ieſus himſelfe, ſhall vſe the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie of Angels, in ſuppreſſing and van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhing the wicked, and in deliuering the godly. And for this cauſe the Apoſtle cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb facs="tcp:2186:18"/> them mightie Angels, becauſe by them and in their miniſterie, the Lord wil ſhew foorth his power and might: Whoſe force no creature is able to reſiſt, whoſe iudgment muſt neceſſarily of all men be endured, and by whoſe ſentence the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſhalbe aſſuredly condemned, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally puniſhed.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8 With a flame of fire, rendering ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance vnto them, who haue not kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen God, and which obey not the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent deſcription of the iudgment tendeth to this end, that the Godly may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that by how much the more feareful the iudgment is which remaineth for their enemies, by ſo much more, the Lord hath a care of their afflictions. For this is the chiefe cauſe of our greefe and ſorrow, that we thinke that God doth ſlightly ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe our miſeries. We doe ſee into what complaints <hi>Dauid</hi> burſteth foorth now and then,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.2.</note> when he fretteth at the pride and inſolencie of his enimies. Therefore the Apoſtle hath vttered all this here for the conſolation of the faithfull, that he diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth the tribunall and iudgment of Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:2186:19"/> to be full of horror. The like deſcription of the comming of Chriſt is ſet downe by the prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 66.15.</note> 
               <hi>Behold the Lord will come with fire, and his charriots like a whirle winde, that he may recompence his anger with wrath, and his indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the flame of fire. &amp;c.</hi> The Lorde Ieſus to be reuealed from heauen with Angels of might, in the flame of fire, ſignifieth that the Lorde Ieſus ſhall come to iudgment with great power and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie in fire.<note place="margin">Mat. 24.30.</note> 
               <hi>For they ſhall ſee the ſonne of man come in the cloudes of heauen with po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and great glorie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 7.21. 2. Pet.. 3.7.</note> God hath once al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready deſtroyed the world with water, the ſecond time he will deſtroy it with fire. But what manner of fire that ſhalbe, and of what matter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pounded, I leaue it to be diſputed of by ſuch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as are fooliſhly curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. It ſhalbe ſufficient for vs only to note this, that Paules purpoſe was to teach, that Chriſt will be a ſeuere reuenger of all thoſe iniuries, which the reprobate do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs: For the metaphor of flame and of fire, is very common in the Scriptures, where the wrath of the Lord is intended.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rendring vengeance vnto them
<pb facs="tcp:2186:19"/> which do not knowe God.</hi> Now it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth to ſhew what the Lord Ieſus will doe when he is reuealed from heauen with angels of his might in the flame of fire: namely, he wil take vengeance of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and vpon ſuch as know not God: that is to ſay, he will plague them in his wrath which wold not know God, but following the world and ſeeking for worldly things, neglected the commaundements of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And which obey not the Goſpell.</hi> By theſe two titles he noteth the vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, who knowe not God, nor obey the Goſpel of Chriſt. For if men do beleue the Goſpell through faith,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.5. and .16.26.</note> vnbeleefe is the cauſe of reſiſting the Goſpell. He condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them alſo of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ignorance of God. For the liuely knowledge of God doth beget of it ſelfe reuerence: but incredulitie is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes blind. Not that the vnbeleuing are altogether void of light &amp; vnderſtanding, but becauſe they haue their minds ſo dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that in ſeeing they cannot ſee.<note place="margin">Eſay. 6.9.</note> Our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt doth not without cauſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, that this is eternal life,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.3.</note> 
               <hi>to know the true God, and Ieſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent.</hi> Therefore of the defect of this moſt
<pb facs="tcp:2186:20"/> holeſome knowledge, followeth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of God, and at the laſt, death. And as it is the office of Chriſt one day to puniſh thoſe which haue not knowne God, ſo alſo it is his office to reward thoſe, which haue knowne God, and which haue obeyed the Goſpell of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9 Which ſhalbe puniſhed with euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting perdition, from the preſence of the Lorde, and from the glorie of his power.</hi> Theſe words appertaine to the amplification of thoſe puniſhments, which perſecutors and al the wicked in general, ſhall one day feele, that no man might thinke that they ſhalbe light or eaſie, or of ſome ſmall continuance. For he ſaith that the perdition ſhal be eternal, that is, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end, a death immortall. To the which ſaying of the Apoſtle agreeth alſo the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Chriſt in his ſermons, where he ſaith that the torments of the wicked ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be perpetuall,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.46.</note> euen as the felicitie of the righteous ſhalbe euerlaſting: ſo that the reprobate ſhall go into eternall torment, and paine,<note place="margin">Mar. 9.44.</note> and the elect into euerlaſting life. And their woorme ſhall not die, and their fire ſhall not be extinguiſhed. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:2186:20"/> the wicked ſhall ſuſteine the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of deſtruction for euer, alwayes fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them, and neuer ceaſing: inſomuch that the very puniſhment it ſelfe ſhal after a ſorte as it were reuiue them, to the end they may alwayes be conſumed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From the preſence of the Lorde.</hi> The perpetuity of death, is proued hereby, that it hath the glorie of Chriſt contrarie vnto it, the which glorie is eternall and hath no ende. Thereupon the horror of the terrible puniſhment may be gathered, becauſe, looke how great the glorie and maieſtie of Chriſt is, ſo great ſhall their torment be. Therefore al they doe deceiue, and are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued themſelues, which doe promiſe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a certaine time, a deliuerance from the torments of hell fire, at which time,<note place="margin">Origens Error.</note> (as <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigen</hi> alſo thought) the wicked and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels themſelues ſhalbe pardoned: but how falſely and wickedly, it doth hereby ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And from the glorie of his power.</hi> With the which power he ſhall come to iudge the quicke and the dead. He allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the forme of the comming of Chriſt to iudgment, and to his might and power,<pb facs="tcp:2186:21"/> before the which the wicked ſhall not be able to ſtand. By theſe woords alſo he ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth how eaſie a matter it is for God to bring torment vpon the wicked. For the Rebellious and obſtinate, ſhalbe tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the terror onely of his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. And contrariwiſe, the preſence of God ſhall bring to the ſaintes felicitie and glorie. For he ſhall come with glorie and with power, inſomuch that neither his glorie ſhall want power, neither ſhall hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preſence and power be without glorie.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10 When he ſhall come to be glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his ſaints, and to be made marue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that beleeue (becauſe our teſtimony toward you was beleued) in that day.</hi> The Apoſtle hauing hitherto ſpoken of the puniſhment of the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, returneth to the godly, and ſaith that Chriſt ſhal come, that he may be glorified in them: that is to ſay, that he may make them to ſhine with his glorie. As if he ſhould ſay, when Chriſt ſhall come to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the impietie of the wicked, he wil then alſo ſhew himſelfe glorious to the ſaints, and will make their vile and corruptible bodies like to his moſt glorious body.<note place="margin">Philip. 3.21.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:2186:21"/> Therefore he will not keepe this glorie to himſelfe alone, but will make the ſame common to al his ſaints. This is the great and ſingular conſolation of the godly, that when the ſonne of God ſhalbe made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in the glorie of his kingdome, he ſhall gather them into the ſame ſocietie with him. And there is in theſe words an <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis</hi> or Compariſon between the preſent ſtate, vnder the which the faithfull doe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and groane, and that laſt reſtitution. For now they are laid open to the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the world: they are counted vile, and of no eſtimation: but then they ſhalbe precious and repleniſhed with glory, when Chriſt ſhall power his glorie vpon them. Therefore to all the godly and ſaintes he ſhall not come auſtere or terrible, but glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and admirable: that they may be led into an inheritance incorruptible.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In all them that beleeue.</hi> This is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for an expoſition. For thoſe whom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had called ſaints, he now calleth beleeuing: ſignifiyng, that there is no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines in men without faith, but that all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deuoid of faith, are prophane and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2186:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Becauſe our teſtimony toward you was beleeued.</hi> That which he ſpake ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally of the ſaintes, he now applieth to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> that they might not doubt them ſelues to be of that number. Becauſe, ſaith he, you beleeued my prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, Chriſt hath now gathered you into the number of his ſaintes, whom he will make partakers of his glorie. Therefore ye ſhalbe ſafe from all thoſe euils, which hang euen ouer the heads of the wicked, and ſhall take hold of them: and they alſo which afore time haue derided you as mad and furious men, ſhall haue you in great admiration. For theſe thinges are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the faithfull for their conſolation, which either haue beene, or are in afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for Chriſtes ſake. He calleth his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine a teſtimony, becauſe the Apoſtles are the witneſſes of Chriſt. Therefore let vs learne, that then the promiſes of God are firme in vs, when we doe ſteedfaſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In that day.</hi> The Apoſtle doth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore repeat this, to reſtraine the deſire o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the faithfull, that they might not be to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haſty. For their life is hidden with God i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2186:22"/> Chriſt:<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.3.</note> but when Chriſt which is our life ſhalbe manifeſted, then ſhall wee alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare with him in glorie. And in another place it is ſaid.<note place="margin">Heb. 10.35.</note> 
               <hi>Knowing in your ſelues, how that ye haue in heauen, a better and an induring ſubſtance. Caſt not therefore away your confidence, which hath great recompence of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. For ye haue need of patience, that after ye haue done the wil of God, ye might receiue the promiſe. For yet a very litle while, and he that ſhal come, will come, and will not tarry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11 Wherefore we alſo pray alwayes for you that our God may make you worthy of his calling, and fulfill all the good pleaſure of his goodnes and the worke of faith with power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the Epilogue, or concluſion of that which goeth before, which conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth of prayer that the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> may be preſerued in that knowledge of ſpirituall thinges, and may growe more and more therein, and proceeding, at the laſt may abide conſtant in the ſame. It is the manner of the Apoſtle in all har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and difficult thinges to adde prayers.
<pb facs="tcp:2186:23"/> prayers. For faith and that reuerence which we beare to the deuine maieſtie, doe teach that the beſt giftes of God muſt be ſought for and gotten by prayers. To the end therefore the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> might know, that they haue need continually of the help of God, he proteſteth that he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for them. As if he ſhould ſay, ye are called by my miniſtery through the Goſpel vnto ſaluation: but yet ye haue need of far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confirmation, namely of ſuch confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, as may make you woorthy of his calling, and to profite and perſeuere in the ſame. For this confirmation and perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, becauſe it is a heauenly gift, I doe diligently praye vnto God to giue it you. And he ſpeaketh of the end and perfect ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment, which conſiſteth in perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance. For God had vouchſafed already to call them. But, we being too ready to fall away, it is no gramarcie to vs, that our vocation is not after that made fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, and ſo ſhould it be in deed, if ſo be God did not eſtabliſhe the ſame in vs. Wherefore it is ſaid that we are counted woorthy, when we come to the full ſcope and perfection. And, if ſo be that our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb facs="tcp:2186:23"/> doth make vs woorthy, to what ende ſhould it be needful to pray vnto the Lord that he would make vs woorthy of his calling? Therefore that worthineſſe doth depend vpon the liberal goodneſſe of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And fulfil al the good pleaſure of his goodneſſe.</hi> The ſecond thing for the which he prayeth for, is the acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhment of the grace and goodneſſe of God. Paul is woonderful in extolling the grace of God. For not being contented that he hath na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his good pleaſure, he ſaith, that the ſame doth ſpring from the goodnes of god.</p>
            <p>Now when we doe heare that the free good pleaſure of God, is the cauſe of our ſaluation, and that the ſame is founded on the grace of God, are we not more then mad if we dare arrogate vnto our merits euen the leaſt thing?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the worke of faith with power.</hi> That is to ſay, that he would finiſh the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry worke of faith through conſtancie and courage of the mind, the which being once by God ſetled in mens mindes, ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth al aduerſities. In theſe words there is no ſmal weight. He might haue ſaid in one word y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your faith may be fulfilled; but he
<pb facs="tcp:2186:24"/> calleth it, good pleaſure. And then he doth proceed further in explayning the matter, that God was by no other means induced the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his goodnes: for in vs he found no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but miſerie. Neither doth Paul aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe the beginning only of our ſaluation to the grace of God, but all the partes thereof alſo. Thus the ſophiſticall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ment and imagination of the ſcoole men is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed, how that wee are preuented by the grace of God, but yet are holpen by me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites following. But Paul in the whole courſe of ſaluation, doth admitte nothing but the mere grace of God. And becauſe the good pleaſure of God is now made perfite, he expoundeth his minde in theſe wordes, <hi>[The worke of faith].</hi> And hee calleth it a work in reſpect of God, which woorketh faith in vs, as if he ſhould ſay, that he may perfect and finiſh the building of faith which he hath begun.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With power.</hi> That is to ſay, effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually. He alludeth vnto the bleſſing or efficacie of God, by which he doth bleſſe and make our faith effectuall. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al he giueth to vnderſtand, that the perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of faith is a great matter, and of great
<pb facs="tcp:2186:24"/> dificultie. The which we finde too true by experience, the reaſon whereof may eaſily be rendered, if we do weigh how great our imbecilitie is, how many lets are thurſt vpon vs from al partes, and alſo how grei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and minifold the temptations of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than be. Therefore except we be woon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully holpen by the power of God, faith ſhall neuer come to her full perfection. For it is as eaſie a matter to finiſhe and make perfect faith in a man, as it is to build a Tower of water, which ſhalbe ſo firme and ſtrong, that it ſhal abide the bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting flouds, and tempeſtious ſtormes, and ſhall reach higher then the cloudes. And we are euen as fluible and vaniſhing as water, as appeareth by theſe woordes of the woman of <hi>Thecoa, we are as wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpilt on the ground,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 14.</note> 
               <hi>which cannot be gathered vp againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12 That the name of our Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt may bee glorified in you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd yee in him, according to the grace of our God, and of the Lorde Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> The Apoſtle had ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed afore what thinges, it is meete
<pb facs="tcp:2186:25"/> for vs to aſke at the handes of God in our prayers. To this admonition he addeth an expoſition of the finall cauſe, why he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the increaſe of faith, and for perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in others, &amp; why he teacheth to pray after his exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple: namely, that the name of Ieſus Chriſt may be glorified in vs, &amp; that we alſo may be glorified by Chriſt, by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> benefite of the grace of our God and of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. The which eſpec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally is to be noted, that they in like maner are to be glorified in Chriſt, which haue ſet foorth his glorie. For firſt of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful goodneſſe of God doth ſhine in this that he wil haue his glorie to be ſeene in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which are couered with reproch &amp; ſham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> But here is a double miracle. He dot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> make vs to ſhine with his glory, euen as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he him ſelfe receiued glory from vs in like manner againe: and therefore he addeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>According to the grace of our God.</hi> For nothing belongeth vnto vs, neither i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the action it ſelfe, nor in the effect and fruit. For our life is framed into the glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie of God, by the onely direction and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ducting of the holy Ghoſt. And wherea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there ſpringeth ſo much fruit from thence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:2186:25"/> we muſt attribute that to the great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God. Neuertheleſſe, if we be not too farre deuoide of ſence, we will thinke it our bounden dutie to endeuour our ſelues all that lieth in vs, to ſet foorth and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce the glorie of Chriſt, the which is alſo ioyned with our glorie. Therfore this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight to be the ſcope and ende of all our good woorkes, that we doe all thinges to the glorie of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. II.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1 NOW we beſeech you, bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, by the comming of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, and by our aſſembling vnto him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>This is the other part of the Epiſtle, which conſiſteth of inſtruction, and exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. For he teacheth euidently by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſignes, when the day of the Lord ſhal come. The <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> had heard in the former Epiſtle, (which he appointed to be read before al men) that the laſt day of the world was not farre off. There were alſo certaine deceiuers, who plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:2186:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2186:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2186:27"/> affirmed, that now already the end of al things was imminent: and ſo they greatly troubled the Church. Wherefore that they might forſake that conceiued opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and vnderſtand the truth, Paul labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, ſhewing what muſt firſt goe before the comming of the Lorde, and with what ſignes and thinges precurrent men are to be forewarned. Theſe ſignes in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are many,<note place="margin">Two ſortes of ſignes which ſhalbe before the iudgment day.</note> and yet of two ſortes, whereof ſome ſhall precurre and be ſeene long before, other ſome ſhall go before his comming to iudgment but a ſhort time. Concerning the ſignes going long before the iudgment daie, our ſauiour Chriſt ſaith:<note place="margin">Mat. 24.37.</note> 
               <hi>As the dayes of Noah were, ſo likwiſe ſhall the comming of the ſonne of man be.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 17.26.</note> 
               <hi>For as in the dayes before the floud, they did eate and drinke, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and giue in marriage, vnto the day that Noe entred into the Arke, and knew nothing till the floud came, and tooke them all away: ſo ſhall alſo the comming of the ſonne of man be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo the Apoſtle ſetteth downe diuers ſignes in his Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy</hi> where he ſaith:<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>Now the ſpirit ſpeaketh eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently,
<pb facs="tcp:2186:27"/> that in the latter times ſome ſhal depart from the faith, and ſhal giue heed vnto ſpirits of error &amp; doctrines of diuels, which ſpeake lyes through hypocriſie, and haue their conſciences burned with a hot iron, forbidding to marry, and commaunding to abſteine from meates. &amp;c.</hi> And in another place he ſayth: <hi>This know,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>that in the Laſt dayes ſhall come perilous times. For men ſhalbe louers of their owne ſelues, couetous, boaſters, proud, curſed ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, diſobedient to parents, vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, vnholy, without naturall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, truce breakers, falſe accuſers, intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, fierce, diſpiſers of them which are good, traytours, heady, high min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, louers of pleaſures more then lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of God, hauing a ſhewe of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but haue denied the power ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</hi> Among theſe ſignes alſo thoſe which Paul reherſeth heere in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> concerning the falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from ſincere doctrine, and the reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of antichriſt, are to be reckoned which ſhall long before the comming of Chriſt to iudgment, be ſeene. The ſignes which
<pb facs="tcp:2186:28"/> ſhalbe more neere the iudgment day, &amp; as it were within the vew of the ſame are theſe:<note place="margin">Mat. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Straight after the tribulation of thoſe dayes, the ſunne ſhalbe darkned, and the moone ſhall looſe her light, and the ſtarres ſhall fall from heauen, and the powers of heauen ſhalbe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and then ſhall the ſigne of the ſon of man appeare in heauen.</hi> How theſe thinges ſhalbe as touching the forme and manner, no man can tel vntil they come to paſſe.<note place="margin">Rom. 11.25.</note> Alſo the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>I would not, brethren, that ye ſhold be ignorant of this ſecret, that partely obſtinacie is come to Iſraell, vntill the fulneſſe of the Gentiles be come in. And ſo all Iſraell ſhalbe ſaued, as it is written: The deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer ſhall come out of Sion, and ſhall turne away the vngodlines from Iacob. &amp;c.</hi> This ſhalbe a preſent ſigne of the comming of the Lorde. But how the ſame ſhall come to paſſe, and which ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be the very moment of the fulfilling of the calling of the Gentils, let him that can, define it. It rather is in vs to wiſh for it, then certainly to appoint the time. <hi>The
<pb facs="tcp:2186:28"/> time will one day come</hi> (ſaith <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine) wherein the calling of the Iewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. 2. Queſt. Euang. cap. 33.</note> 
               <hi>in the ſauing health of the Goſpell, ſhalbe manifeſt.</hi> But when, and how the ſame ſhalbe, he doth not expreſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the comming of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> The Apoſtle in theſe wordes doth adiure the faithfull by the comming of Chriſt, that they doe not raſhly beleeue the day of the ſame to be preſent, and to thinke no otherwiſe of it then religiouſly and ſoberly. As if he ſhould ſay, as the comming of Chriſt is a thing very preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vnto you, by which he ſhall gather vs together vnto himſelfe, and ſhall in very deed perfect and accompliſh the vnitie of the bodie, which as yet imperfectly we im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace by faith: euen ſo by the ſame I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you be not to light of credit, if ſome by one collour or other, do affirme that the ſame day is preſent. But as ſome in the Apoſtles time, were to ready to beleue the preſent comming of Chriſt, which gaue Paul occaſion to write this exhortation ſo it is greatly to be feared, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in this age there are many Epicures, which offend in
<pb facs="tcp:2186:29"/> the other extremitie, and liuing in ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, doe contemne as a fable thoſe thinges which in the Scriptures are ſpoken of the comming of Chriſt to iudgment: againſt whom the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> writeth this: <hi>There ſhall come in the laſt dayes, moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers which will walke after their owne luſtes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>and ſay, where is the promiſe of his comming? For ſince the fathers died, all thinges continue in the ſame eſtate wherein they were at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp;c.</hi> Wherefore as men ought not to be light of credit, to beleeue thoſe vaine i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations of ſuch as are fooliſhly cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in pointing out the times and moments of times, which God hath by his prerogatiue reſerued from the knowledge of mortall men to himſelfe alone: ſo on the contrarie part they ought to beware of that ſecuritie which made the fooliſh vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to be ſecluded from the ioye of the bridgrome,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> and to be vigilant, becauſe they know neither the day nor the houre. <hi>2 That yee be not ſodenly moued from your minde, nor troubled, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſpirite, nor by worde, nor by letter, as it were from vs, as though the
<pb facs="tcp:2186:29"/> day of Chriſt were at hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this worde <hi>[mind]</hi> he vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a ſound faith, which is grounded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wholeſome doctrine. For they had beene carried and rapt as it were into a traunce and aſtoniſhment by this forged imagination, which the Apoſtle reiecteth. He reherſeth here three kindes of deceit, of the which he would haue the <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> to take heed. The firſt of which, is this: <hi>Neither by ſpirit:</hi> That is to ſay, by reuelation, or propheſie, by which, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly men haue deceiued many, boaſting of the ſpirit of God, when as they were led by their wicked deſires and luſtes. They knew that the name of the ſpirite was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, and that it brought great autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and credit to propheſiyng. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the manner of the Diuell is,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.14.</note> to tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſforme himſelfe into an Angel of light, ſo the deceiuers had ſtollen this title to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the ſimple withall. And although Paul might haue pulled this viſor from their face, yet he thought it better by way of conceſſion to ſpeake thus: As if he ſhould ſay, howſoeuer they pretend to haue the ſpirite of reuelation, yet beleeue them
<pb facs="tcp:2186:30"/> not: according to the ſaying of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Prooue the ſpirits whether they be of God or no.</hi> With ſuch a ſpirite, ſometime the <hi>Montaniſtes,</hi> and <hi>Valenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> and now the <hi>Catabaptiſtes,</hi> were and are endued, by which they haue great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deceiued the ſimple. Therfore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle would not haue the faithfull to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from holeſome doctrine,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note> though an Angell come from heauen and teache o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then he hath taught already.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor by worde.</hi> The other kinde of deceit is by worde, that is to ſay, by doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine deliuered by the mouth, the which if it be furniſhed with eloquence and proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, it is moſt peſtilent. Such are thoſe ſophiſticall deceiuers, which gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to and fro, from place to place, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out calling, doe cauſe great ſturre, and doe greatly trouble the godly preachers, and are therefore aptly termed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: which ſignifieth a ſubtill kinde of deceiuers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor by letter.</hi> The third kind of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite is, by counterfeit Epiſtles or wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. For it is the manner of wranglers to counterfeit an Epiſtle vnder the name of ſome excellent man, to the end they may
<pb facs="tcp:2186:30"/> deceiue, and may get that commended by the authority of man, which els comming naked, would not be receiued. Hereby the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it doth appeare, that this impudency hath beene practiſed long ſince, to counterfeite the names of other men: Whereby the mercy of God toward vs appeareth the greater and more woonderful, that Paul being yet liuing, and ſeeing his name falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuſed in forged writings, his Epiſtles notwithſtanding haue been preſerued ſafe and ſound vntil this age. Verily this could not ſo come to paſſe neither by chance, nor yet by the induſtry of men, if ſo be God by his power, had not ſuppreſſed Sathan and al his miniſters. By this ſathanical prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, which Paul here condemneth, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be told how filthily certaine lewd var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets haue deluded the Church of God, who haue thruſt vpon vs many bookes, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie moe Epiſtles and decretals, as if they had come from the Apoſtles, or from Apoſtolicall men, or elſe from ſuch writers as were had in greate eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, for their learning and holineſſe: which writinges notwithſtanding theſe good men neuer knewe, and if they were
<pb facs="tcp:2186:31"/> liuing would neuer allow. For there are carried about,<note place="margin">Canons and Decretals of Rome.</note> certaine Canons of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, certaine Epiſtles of Apoſtolicall men, and many other bookes beſide, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the name of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> or <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> which bookes theſe men neuer ſaw. And yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding there want not ſome, who taking this place for their ground and warrant, will thurſt vpon the Church of God whatſoeuer they liſt, obiecting that all thinges are not reuealed in the Scriptures, which are neceſſarily requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to true pietie and godlineſſe: becauſe mention is here made of ſpirite, of worde, and of an Epiſtle by which (ſay they) a more abſolute doctrine hath beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed to poſterities. But theſe men do not ſee, that this ſame very place doth fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warne men, that they be not ſeduced from a ſound faith already receiued, by the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of men; which theſe men couering with the viſor of ſpirit, worde, and of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, decretal, or of Apoſtolical, and moſt holy, doe enforce vpon vs. For thus they offer vnto vs their Maſſes and all other thinges, which they are not able to prooue by the teſtimonies of Scriptures, erneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:2186:31"/> affirming y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were iuſtified by Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tolical tradition, &amp; afterward confirmed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth by the Epiſtles of Apoſtolicall men, &amp; alſo by the reuelation of the holy Ghoſt. Let vs therefore beware of theſe rauenous woolues,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.15.</note> which being couered with ſheep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kinnes, doe come to no other ende, but to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rouble, rent, and deuoure. Let vs faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ully hold and keepe the minde of Chriſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd the ſound and Apoſtolicall groundes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f holeſome and true religion. So ſhal we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e deceiued by no manner of meanes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As though the day of Chriſt were at hande.</hi> This place ſemeth to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rarie to many other places of Scripture, where the holy Ghoſt doth pronounce that day to be at hande. But they are eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled, for in reſpect of God it is at hand,<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.4. 2. Pet. 3.8.</note> with whom one day is as a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d yeers, &amp; a thouſand yeers as one day. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les the Lord would haue vs daily to wait &amp; looke for the ſame, &amp; not to appoint vnto our ſelues a certaine time. <hi>Watch</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt) <hi>for ye knowe not when the time is.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 13.33</note> But theſe falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, whom Paul confuteth, ſeeing it ſtood them vpon to hold mens mindes in
<pb facs="tcp:2186:32"/> ſuſpence, leaſt they ſhuld be wearied with the tediouſnes of delay, commanded them to be careleſſe concerning the ſhort &amp; ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy comming of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3 Let no manne deceiue you by anye meanes: for that day ſhall not come, except there come a departing firſt, &amp; that that man of ſinne be diſcloſed, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the ſonne of perdition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Paul againe admoniſheth the <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians</hi> to beware that they bee not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, that hee might make them the more vigilaunt and heedefull to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and that he might diſcourage and diſmay thoſe whiche laye in wayte to hurt the ſimplicitie of ſuch as beleeued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That daie ſhal not come, except</hi> To the end the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> might not in vayne promiſe to them ſelues that the day of their redemption was at hande, he propoundeth vnto them a lamentable propheſie of the defection and diſſipation of the Churche to come. This agreeth with that ſermon of Chriſt, which he made vnto his Diſciples, when they queſtioned with him of the ende of the worlde. For
<pb facs="tcp:2186:32"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e exhorteth them to prepare themſelues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o harde conflictes. And after that hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath ſpoken of great and ſtrange calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies, with the which the earth ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell neere waſted and ſpoyled,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.</note> hee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth that the ende commeth not yet, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat theſe thinges are the beginninges of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orrowes. After the ſame manner Paul <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lſo pronounceth, that the faithfull muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight a long time before they can obtayne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Crowne.</p>
            <p>But the defection or departure, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Greeke is called <hi>Apoſtaſia,</hi> ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th a flying or running away, like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o that of ſouldiers, which forſake theyr Captayne, or of ſubiectes which refuſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o yeeld their due obedience to the ciuill Magiſtrate and ordinarie power. Euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o in like maner when the fault of defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, is committed in the Church, a two fold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reaſon is committed. The firſt is, when men depart from the fayth of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the Goſpel. For we are ſo tied to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem, that we ought not to forſake them: &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n like maner we haue God through them fauourable vnto vs, and at the laſt bound
<pb facs="tcp:2186:33"/> vnto vs. The ſecond is when the du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> woorſhippe of God, which he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, is forſaken, or by any manner of meanes violated. For by faith in Chriſt we are made Chriſtians and the people of God: from the which when we doe fall, we are made runawayes, Apoſtataes, and whatſoeuer elſe, ſaue the people o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God. In like manner they which depar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from the obedience of Gods commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, are rightly called the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the wicked: and the name of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, or of the people of God, cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended rightly to apperteine vnto them. And the wickedneſſe of either of theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections is encreaſed, when the profeſſion of ſtrange woorſhippings is ioyned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, of the which God hath commaunded nothing at all: eſpecially when they are fained to be done to the honour of him, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when they are ſaid to be ſuch as deſeru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the fauour of God, and of the gifts of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes and of euerlaſting life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or elſe when they are affirmed to be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſarie, and ſuch as cannot be omitted with out ſinne. For they are contrarie to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> faith in Chriſt, and to that woorſhippe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2186:33"/> which God himſelfe hath commaunded. This therfore is a notable place and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be marked. This was a ſore and perilous temptation, which might quaile the moſt couragious, to ſee the Church which with ſo great labors, by little &amp; lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle &amp; very hardly was erected in a meane eſtate, ſodenly as ſhaken downe with a tempeſt, to fall. Paul therefore doth afore hand arme, not onely the mindes of the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> but alſo of all the godly, that when it ſhall befall the Church to be diſſipated and ſcattered, they be not terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied as with a new and ſtrang thing.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the interpreters haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly wreſted this place, we muſt firſt of all indeuour to get the true and proper meaning of the Apoſtle. He demeth that the day of Chriſt ſhall come before ſuch time as the world ſhalbe fallen into <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie</hi> or defection, and the kingdome of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhall haue gotten place in the Church. That properly is not the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, when as there ſhalbe a departing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>way from the Roman Empire, as many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue thought:<note place="margin">Apoſtaſie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined.</note> but <hi>Apostaſie</hi> or defection <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a departure from the faith in Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:2186:34"/> and from the puritie of the Euangelicall doctrine, and a declining to falſe worſhip, according to the fantaſies of men. And thus they are Apoſtataes, which forſake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſtian faith, ſeruing idols, and deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelues with ceremonies deuiſed by men.<note place="margin">Exod. 32.6.</note> Euen as when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſraelites wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the Golden calfe, being wearied with the long abſence of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from the preſcript law of God, beca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e Apoſtataes. Paul therfore calleth a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous defection from God, apoſtaſie, and the ſame not to be of one man or of a fewe, but ſuch a defection as extendeth it ſelfe farre and wide in the greater multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of men. For ſeeing the apoſtaſie is named without any addition, it cannot be reſtrayned vnto a fewe. Now, no other can be vnderſtood to be Apoſtataes, but ſuch as haue afore time giuen their names to Chriſt and to his Goſpell. Paul there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore foreſheweth a certein generall defec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the viſible Church: as if he ſhould ſay, the Church muſt be brought into foule and horrible decay, before the full reſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring thereof doe come. Hereby we may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily gather, how profitable this Propheſie
<pb facs="tcp:2186:34"/> of Paul is. For it might haue ſeemed not to haue beene the Lordes buylding, which ſodainly was ouerthrowen, which lay ſo long t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me in ruine and decay, if ſo be Paul had not long-before ſhewed, that this ſhuld come to paſſe.<note place="margin">Theſe 400. yeeres are to be accounted from the time of Pope Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory the 7. vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the time of Martin Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. From Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the 7. to this preſent yeere are expired, 511. yeeres, or thereabout.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, many men at this day, waying with themſelues the long time of the Churches declining and deſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> which continued by the ſpace of <hi>400.</hi> yeers at the leaſt, doe beginne to wauer and doubt, as if this came not to paſſe by the determination and counſell of God. The Papiſtes to couer the tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nie of their idol y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope, make this excuſe, that it could not be, that Chriſt would ſo long time forſake his Church. But the weake haue here wherewith to ſuſteine themſelues, when they doe heare that the deformitie of the Church which they behold, was ſo long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe foreſhewed. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> impudencie of the Papiſtes is manifeſtly conuinced, becauſe the Apoſtle pronounceth that there ſhall come a defection, when the worlde is brought vnder the gouernment of Chriſt. So that the defection is a treacherous falſehood, by which men depart from the
<pb facs="tcp:2186:35"/> Chriſtian faith, and from the woorſhippe which God hath commaunded, or elſe when ſtraung and Phariſeicall woorſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings are inſtituted. And it was meete that ſuch a defection ſhould be admitted by the ſubtil practiſes of deceiuers, (which preach and teach wicked thinges) before ſuch time as Chriſt ſhould come, for a puniſhment to the vnthankfull and vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing, but to the godly, for a triall and exerciſe of their faith. Whereby alſo a way was made to <hi>Antichriſt</hi> to inuade the Church, and to oppreſſe the libertie of the ſame, and that enimie of the Churches of Chriſt and aduerſarie vnto God, raygn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the defection grewe more and more. For he came to ſeduce &amp; deſtroy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world with the woorkes of error. The fault of of this ſpirituall defection is alſo ſpoken of by Chriſt in theſe woordes;<note place="margin">Luke. 18.8. Act. 20.29. 2. Pet. 2.1. Iude. a. 4. 1. Tim. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>When the ſonne of man commeth, thinke ye that he ſhall finde faith on the earth?</hi> The authors and maiſters of which Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie in the Church, are the profeſſors of falſe doctrine. Concerning whom the A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſtles ſpoke many things aforehand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And that that man of ſinne be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2186:35"/> The Apoſtle here putteth down two ſignes of the comming of Chriſt, namely, a departure from ſincere doctrine and from the true vnderſtanding of whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome doctrine: and a reuelation of that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection or departing. What he ment by the former ſigne we haue already ſhewed. Now we muſt intreate of the latter ſigne, that is to ſay, of the reuelation and origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> And to the end the diſciphering of this beaſt and monſter, may appeare the more plaine, we wil firſt begin to deſcribe the place: ſecondly,<note place="margin">Antichriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by 3. thinges.</note> the perſon with his names, and thirdly his qualities.</p>
            <p>The place and ſeate of this monſter <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> is <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Italie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The place or ſeat of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</note> as ſhalbe proued by the <hi>17.</hi> chapter of the Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of S. Iohn, the <hi>9.</hi> verſe, where the Angell expounding to ſaint Iohn the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of the beaſt with ſeuen heades, eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently declareth, that thoſe ſeuen heades doe ſignifie ſeuen hils, whereon the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſitteth. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n this being manifeſt, that the woman ſignifieth a great Citie. Let vs ſee where we can finde a great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie builded vpon ſeuen hils, and that by
<pb facs="tcp:2186:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> the interpretation of the Angell is,<note place="margin">Rome is Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</note> 
               <hi>Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> or <hi>Rome,</hi> the ſeate of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> Now in all the world, there is not a Citie to be found builded vpon ſeuen hils, but <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> which all writers, Poets, Hiſtoriers, Coſmographers, with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent doe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe to be <hi>Rome,</hi> which is buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>7.</hi> hils, whoſe names are theſe: <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinus, Capitolinus, Auentinus, Exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus, Viminalis, Quirinalis</hi> and <hi>Caeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi> This is ſo euident a demonſtration of <hi>Rome</hi> to be <hi>Babilon,</hi> builded on <hi>7.</hi> hils, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Angel could not more plainely haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed <hi>Rome</hi> though he had named her. But if any man vpon peeuiſh obſtinacie will except, that the worde of hils haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſignification, and are taken meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorically for ſome other thing, he may eaſily be conuinced by this reaſon: that this interpretation of the Angell muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be plaine and eaſie to be vnderſtood, or elſe it deſerueth not the name of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation. Therefore if the Angell go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about to expound the miſterie of the ſeuen heades, giueth this expoſition that they ſignifie ſeuen hils: if hils be not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in their proper ſence, to what purpoſe
<pb facs="tcp:2186:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſerueth this expoſition? For if the name of hils hath neede of another expoſition, he had beene as good to haue left the name of heads vnexpounded. Therefore except we will ſay, that the interpretation of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell is in vaine, we muſt needes confeſſe that hils are taken in their proper ſence for hils, and then the Citie builded vpon ſeuen hils, without all controuerſie, is the Citie of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer in the laſt verſe of the <hi>17.</hi> Chapter of Iohns Reuelation, the Angel in plaine wordes ſaith, that the woman which Saint Iohn ſaw, (which was the great whoore of <hi>Babylon</hi>) is that great Citie, whiche hath dominion ouer the kings of the earth. What braſen face is ſo impudent as to deny that <hi>Rome</hi> was that great Citie, which had dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the kinges of the earth at that time when this was ſpoken? Or what other Citie had dominion ouer the kinges of the earth in ſaint Iohns time but <hi>Rome?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> a moſt ancient doctor of the Church, the ſcholler of <hi>Policarpe,</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licarpe</hi> of Saint Iohn, diſputing of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt,</hi> ſawe him no where elſe, but in the
<pb facs="tcp:2186:37"/> Citie of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>The numbring of the beaſtes name by the greeke letters.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>λ</cell>
                           <cell>30.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>α</cell>
                           <cell>1.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>τ</cell>
                           <cell>300.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>ε</cell>
                           <cell>5.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>ι</cell>
                           <cell>10.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>ν</cell>
                           <cell>50.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>ο</cell>
                           <cell>70.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>ς</cell>
                           <cell>200.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Tertul. aduerſ. Martion. lib. 3.</p>
               </note> And therefore he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring the laſt verſe of the <hi>13.</hi> chapter of the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> where it is ſaid that the number of the beaſts name, is ſixe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, ſixtie and ſixe, ſheweth that the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of many in his tyme was, that ſeeing this name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which in Engliſh ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth the <hi>Latine</hi> man, or <hi>Romane,</hi> in the numeral Greeke letters, it contayneth this number, that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> muſt be ſought at <hi>Rome.</hi> This opinion of <hi>Irenae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> is about <hi>14.</hi> hundred yeres old. <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> alſo a very auncient writer plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirmeth, that <hi>Babilon</hi> ſignifieth <hi>Rome.</hi> And <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> vpon this Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> ſaith thus, <hi>Towards the declyning of the Romane Empire, Antichriſt ſhall comme, and not without cauſe. For ſo long as this Empire ſhall floriſh, none will eaſily be ſubiect vnto it. But this being deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he ſhal inuade the power of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire being void, and ſhal take it to him ſelfe, inſomuch as he will take vppon him the Empire both of God &amp; men. For as all kingdomes which were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Romane Empire, were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed:
<pb facs="tcp:2186:37"/> euen ſo ſhall the kingdome of the Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s be deſtroyed by Antichriſt. S. Hierome</hi> alſo writing to <hi>Marcella:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hier. in prefat. lib. de ſancto. ſpirit.</note> 
               <hi>This Babylon</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and this whoore clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with purple, which is painted foorth vnto vs in the Apocalyps, can ſignifie no other thing vnto vs then Rome.</hi> And <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Auſt. lib. 18. de ciuit. Dei. cap 2.</note> 
               <hi>Babylon is the firſt Rome,</hi> and <hi>Rome the ſecond Babylon.</hi> By theſe &amp; other teſtimonies of old writers, which might be alleaged, it is manifeſtly proued, that <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Italie</hi> is <hi>Babylon,</hi> the ſeate of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the perſon of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> there haue bene diuers fantaſies and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, ſome by a fooliſhe opinion haue thought that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhuld be one onely man, which ſhould come of the tribe of <hi>Dan,</hi> and ſhould be borne in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and ſhoulde raigne certeine yeeres, to the great detrement and hurt of the faithfull. Some haue deemed <hi>Mahomet</hi> to be this <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> who hath alienated his <hi>Turks</hi> from Chriſt. Otherſome haue dreamed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Nero</hi> was tranſlated out of the woorlde to come againe an <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> with his tiranny to vexe the Church. But Paul doth not ſpeake here of one man, but of a
<pb facs="tcp:2186:38"/> kingdome which Sathan ſhall inioy and poſſeſſe,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.15.</note> that he may ſet vp the ſeat of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homination in the middeſt of Gods tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Now, it is manifeſt that the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Emperours <hi>Nero</hi> &amp; the reſt, did not ſit in the Church of God: therfore the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Emperour is not this <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> And by the ſame reaſon it is manifeſt that <hi>Mahomet</hi> is not that eſpecial <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> becauſe he ſitteth without the temple of God. Againe it is manifeſt in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhould deceiue the worlde with falſe doctrine, vnder pretence and colour of true religion, and therefore ſo often times the ſcripture forewarneth men that they bee not ſeduced by him, which were needleſſe, if any open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed enemie of Chriſt ſhuld be that <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</hi> For there is no liklihood, that an heathen man, a Iew, or a Turk, ſhould deceiue any multitude of true Chriſtians: but he that vnder the pretence of the name of Chriſt ſeeketh moſt of all to deface the honour of Chriſt: he is a very ſubtill ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie, and the very ſpirit of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt:</hi> as Saint Iohn alſo in his Epiſtle doth teſtifie. For in the ſecond Chapter
<pb facs="tcp:2186:38"/> ſpeaking of thoſe <hi>Antichriſtes</hi> which were the forerunners of that great <hi>Antichriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 2.</note> he ſheweth that they went out from the Church:<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 4.</note> and in the fourth Chapter he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them falſe Prophets, and teacheth men how to know the ſpirit of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> namely thus, <hi>He that denieth Ieſus to be Chriſt: He that denieth Ieſus Chriſt to be come in the fleſh.</hi> That is to ſay, he that derogateth any thing from the honor of Ieſus to bee Chriſt, and in his fleſhe to haue performed the full worke of mans re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption (as the Pope doth moſt blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly) he is <hi>Antichriſt:</hi> and who ſo tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth any ſuch doctrine, ſpeaketh by the ſpirite of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore this kingdome of abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, is deſcribed to vs vnder the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of one, becauſe the kingdom is one, how ſoeuer they ſucceſſiuely ſucceede one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Whereupon Saint Auguſtine ſaith,<note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. 20. de ciuit. Dei. cap. 19</note> 
               <hi>Antichriſt ſhall come towarde the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Romaine Empire, and hee ſhall not be a prince, or one man alone, but a multitude of men are belonging vnto him, who together with him ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be called Antichriſt, and he ſhall ſitte in
<pb facs="tcp:2186:39"/> the temple of God, as though he and his were the Church of God it ſelfe.</hi> And in an other place,<note place="margin">Idem. lib. de Antichriſto.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhal renue ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, he ſhal ſcater the doctrine of the Goſpell: and to this end he ſhal keepe Magicians, coniurers and enchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ters. &amp;c.</hi> Now, euery one knoweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> falſ mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, wherwith he hath abuſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, to lead them away from Chriſt. And he that will ſee how many of the Popes came to their Popedome, by magicke and ſorcery, let him reade y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which their owne ſtorie writers haue written therof: as <hi>Cardinal Benno, Peter</hi> the monk, <hi>Volateran, Sabel licus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Platina.</hi> Thus then we ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt</hi> is not one man alone, which muſt come at one inſtant of time, but is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, ſeat, and ſucceſſion of men, an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire lifted vp againſt Ieſus Chriſt. And for this cauſe he is called <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> that is to ſay, contrarie to Chriſt the mediator, and not ſimplely againſt God. For as he is called <hi>Antiſtrategos,</hi> not only which ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him ſelfe againſt his captaine, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo which taketh vpon him the place &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the captaine, being in deed but a baſe ſouldier: euen ſo he is <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> which is an aduerſary, and yet taketh vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:2186:39"/> him to be the vicar of Chriſt. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle alſo in this Epiſtle calleth him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The man of ſin.</hi> Becauſe he is both ſin, and a ſinner, and an occaſion to others to ſin, and which maketh others, yea infinit numbers to ſinne. He calleth him alſo</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſonne of Perdition.</hi> Whereby he meaneth that <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> is not onely of himſelfe euill, wicked, ſinfull, prophane, &amp; far from all goodnes, and ſo the ſonne of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting perdition, but alſo a deceiuer, &amp; to the faith &amp; manners of an innumerable ſort, an offence, &amp; ſo the author and cauſe of their perditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whom he ſeduceth from the way of truth and of righteouſnes. For he is in all things contrary to Chriſt. In pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate &amp; perſonal wickedneſſes, he is hurtful to himſelfe onely, ſauing that he is enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced through his owne wickedneſſe to be hurtfull to others alſo. Therfore we muſt know, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is a certaine publike miſchiefe and peſtilent cto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>agion, that doth inuade and raigne in the Church of God.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4 Which is an aduerſary, and exalteth himſelfe againſt al that is called God, or that is worſhipped: ſo that he doth ſit as God in the temple of God, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe that he is God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2186:40"/>
            <p>In theſe words the Apoſtle Paul doth paint forth vnto vs as in a table,<note place="margin">The qualities of Antichriſt.</note> the liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Image of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> in his qualities. By which woordes wee may alſo gather what his kingdome is, and in what things it doth conſiſt. Hee attributeth to <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt</hi> three vices eſpecially, namely: To be an aduerſarie vnto God, and his diuine doctrine: Not to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented with the true worſhip of God: And to be proud &amp; to rule ouer faith, as if he were ſome God. For as the kingdome of Chriſt is ſpirituall, ſo this tyranny muſt needes bee ouer mens ſoules, that hee may bee contrary to the kingdome of Chriſt. Therefore that thou maieſt the better knowe <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> ſet Chriſt ouer againſt him. For he is an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary vnto Chriſt vnder whoſe tyrannie &amp; execrable dominion, they doe liue, which deſpiſing the ſimplicitie and trueth of the Goſpell of Chriſt, may giue credit to wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and diueliſh deluſions. Such are they that deny remiſſion of ſinnes to ſuch as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent: which aſcribe ſaluation to their goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> works: which haue falſely forged y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſins are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>purged w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> purgatory fire: whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> diſgrace the authority of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture: whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2186:40"/> preferre Councelles, Archbiſhops, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Biſhops, before the canonicall ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: which take libertie to them ſelues to adde to, or to ſubtract from the worde of God: which put no difference between the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologicall or diuine, and philoſophical ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges: which preferre an olde cuſtome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the worde of God: which boldly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that an aſſembly of Biſhops is the Churche: which ſaie that their Church ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre: which earneſtly mainteine that the keyes of bynding and looſing are gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the whole churche: which build the Church vpon Peter, and not vppon the rocke Chriſt: which will haue the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie of the Church a Lordſhip, and not a miniſterie: which make their Pope a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Biſhops for the mainteinaunce of tyranny: which in making and appointing of Biſhops, require the iudgment of cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers onelie: which ſcorne this, that all Chriſtians are kings and prieſtes, as from that number exempted: which condemne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he marriage of the miniſters of the word, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it were with the Cenſors authoritie: which doe not ſee, that their good workes whatſoeuer, without faith, are ſin: which
<pb facs="tcp:2186:41"/> do not leaue the pardoning of ſins to God alone, and to his worde: which make ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner of ſatiſfaction in repentance then Chriſt himſelfe hath done: which doe allow that the maſſe is a ſacrifice, &amp; a iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifiing good woorke: which pronounce that Chriſt died only for originall ſinne, and not for all ſinnes in generall: which ſing dyrges for dead mens ſpirits: which haue iudged that remiſſion of ſins is to be redeemed with buying of indulgences, &amp; by going on pilgrimages: which alter the inſtitution of Chriſt in the Lords ſupper: which abuſe excommunications for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe, then to make the penitent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner confeſſe his ſinne: which in matters and cauſes of faith, quite without the reach of humane reaſon, doe attribute a certaine ſtrength to free will, that is to the will and power of men: which will not haue men iuſtified before God by faith on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: which giue great and diuine honour to pictures &amp; images of ſaints: which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend that it is neceſſary for the obtayning of euerlaſting life, to make choiſe of dayes &amp; of meates: which flatter themſelues that
<pb facs="tcp:2186:41"/> they are able to fulfill the lawe of God without Chriſt: which make a lawe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning virginitie and ſingle life: which doe not thinke that chaſtitie is the gift of God: which forbid oathes in cauſes of faith, and godlineſſe: which torment mens conſciences with humane precepts: which diſcharge ſubiects of their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnto maieſtrates. The teachers and defenders of theſe and ſuch like opinions, which are contrarie to the worde of God, are Apoſtataes, &amp; the followers of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</hi> The increace of theſe kind of men, is a plaine token that the laſt day appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And exalteth him ſelfe againſt all that is called God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Pride of Antichriſt.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The other wicked qualitie of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> is, to extoll himſelfe aboue all that is called God. By which Paul meaneth that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhall violently take to himſelfe thoſe thinges which are proper to God alone, as, to exalt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe aboue all that is called God, or that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> woorſhipped, that religion and the whole woorſhippe of God, may lie vnder his feete. For the Apoſtle doth not
<pb facs="tcp:2186:42"/> ſpeake here of the name of God, but of his maieſty and worſhip, and ſo generally of al thoſe thinges which God chalengeth to himſelfe. As if Paul had ſaid, That is true religion, by which the true God alone is worſhipped. This religion the ſon of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition tranſferreth vnto him ſelfe. Now whoſoeuer he be that hath learned out of the Scriptures, what thinges are moſt proper vnto God, and ſhall on the contrary part behold and conſider, what the pope vſurpeth to himſelfe, although he be but a child of ten yeeres of age, he ſhall take no great paines in learning to knowe <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 33.22. Iames. 4.12</note> The Scripture pronounceth that God alone is the Lawe-maker: who can ſaue and deſtroy: the onely king to whom it belongeth to rule and gouerne mens ſoules by his word. It teacheth that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes and ſaluation are to be ſought at the handes of Chriſt and no where els: and it ſheweth the manner &amp; way how. There is none of theſe thinges which the Pope doth not challenge to himſelfe, in waye of his right. He boaſteth that it is in his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to binde mens conſciences with wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lawes he luſteth, and to ſubiect them to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall
<pb facs="tcp:2186:42"/> puniſhments. He is woorſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of kings as a good and faithfull Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor of the Church, he being a moſt wicked deceiuer. And although he performeth no one duty of a good ſhepeheard, but doth all things contrary to the duty of a good Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, yet he is proclaymed the moſt holy &amp; moſt vigilant Paſtor of the Church, yea, which is more, the Lorde and head of the Church, who hath authoritie and power to preſcribe articles of faith, and to make new lawes for the performing of them, But he condemneth the true and pure doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Goſpell as wicked and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, ſo farre off is he, from healing any man with the doctrine and conſolations thereof, and from inuiting any one to true and chriſtian repentance. And yet for all this, it is not lawfull for any man to ſay without perill, ſo much as, why doeſt thou doe this? But he hath at hand thoſe which will defend him that he doth all things wel, and which wil be ready ſeuere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to puniſhe thoſe which ſhall reprehend him. Theſe are called inquiſitors of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall wickedneſſe, which will not ſuffer a man ſo much as to mutter againſt the
<pb facs="tcp:2186:43"/> Pope: who notwithſtanding fayneth ſinne where there is no ſinne, and proclameth rightuouſneſſe where there is none at all. He either appointeth new Sacraments at his pleaſure, or elſe he corrupteth thoſe which Chriſt hath already inſtituted. And why not if it be true which one hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the Parliament of Popes at-<hi>Rome.</hi> That God holdeth for well done, all that is done of the Pope:<note place="margin">Popiſh blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies.</note> that his will is the rule of all right and righteouſneſſe: that he can abſolutely doe in this worlde all that God can doe, ſeeing he is all, and aboue all thinges: that if he chaunge his purpoſe, it is to be preſumed, that God chaungeth his: that his power extendeth it ſelfe to heauen and to earth, yea and downe to hel: that none may appeale from him to God: that he may ordaine againſt the Epiſtles of ſaint Paul, as greater then ſaint Paul, and againſt the olde Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, as greater then any authors ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And yet one, hath gone further, who hath diſputed whether he may ordaine any thing contrarie to the Goſpel, whether he haue not more power then Peter: whether he were ſimplely a man, or as God. To
<pb facs="tcp:2186:43"/> be breefe, the Diuell hath gone ſo farre in this miſterie of iniquitie, that another diſputed in the ſcooles not long afore <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> time, whether the Pope did not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate in both natures, the diuine and humane, with Ieſus Chriſt. What I pray you is to exalt it ſelfe aboue all that is called God, if it be not this, which is done by the Pope and his miniſters?</p>
            <p>The Pope ſpoyling and robbing God after this manner of his honor, leaueth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him nothing but a bare and naked title, tranſferring his whole power vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. And this is euen that which Paul now addeth, ſaying,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So that he doth ſit as God in the Temple of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Apoſtle doth more openly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pride of <hi>Antichriſt. Antichriſt</hi> ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the temple of God, becauſe he hath his kingdome in the ſame: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the falſe Prophet and the deceiuer, he doth inwardly commaund the Church, and playeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king, or rather y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyrant, where he ought not. Such a kingdome hath not <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>homet,</hi> nor the Turke (as is already ſaid) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may be either ſaid or thought to be the
<pb facs="tcp:2186:44"/> kingdome of Chriſt, or of the Church of Chriſt, for that kingdome hath beene got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and enlarged hitherto by warres and by ſeditions, and he doth ſet vpon the Church without. But the dominion of the Pope conſtituted and erected by fraud and ſuperſtition, is ſaid to be the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Church, of the elect, of God, and of Chriſt Ieſus: and he by his tiran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and iniquitie doth ſpoile all thinges belonging to Chriſtian religion. He is thought to be a godly Paſtor, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together a theefe, a ſpoyler, and a moſt greedy rauening woolfe. In theſe fewe words of Paul, their error or rather wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full blindneſſe is ſufficiently confuted, who will haue the Pope therefore to be Chriſtes vicar, becauſe he hath his place and ſeate in the Church by long ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, how wickedly ſoeuer he behaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. For Paul doth not place <hi>Antichriſt</hi> elſewhere then in the very ſanctuary of God, becauſe he is no forraine, but a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtical enemy which is an aduerſary vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt vnder the name of Chriſt. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, or rather the hearts of Chriſtians, are the temples of God,<note place="margin">Iohn. 14.23</note> as appeareth by
<pb facs="tcp:2186:44"/> ſundry teſtimonies of Scripture.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.16. 2. Cor. 6.16.</note> In this temple of God <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſitteth, when he bindeth their conſciences with his lawes: when he commaundeth, dayes, and monethes, and times to be kept: when he wil haue ſome dayes to be faſted, and ſome to be kept holy, vpon paine of diſpleaſure of the omnipotent God, and of the bleſſed Apoſtles Peter and Paul. He putteth great holineſſe in veſtments, in ſhauen crouns, in chaunting of quiremen, in ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of temples, in vnctions, and ſuch like. In the obſeruation of ſuch thinges, he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth men to put their confidence, and for the neglecting of theſe thinges, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth them to repent. To ſuch as keepe his ſtatutes he giueth fat benefices, prebends and dignities, maiſterſhippe, and doctorſhip, with ſeraphicall holines, large indulgences, a yeere of iubile, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing remiſſion of all their ſinnes, and euerlaſting life: but ſuch as keepe not his lawes, he depriueth of their goods, of all honor, baniſheth them (if it were poſſible) out of the worlde, he killeth them, he curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them, and adiudgeth them to eternall damnation, although they haue kept (if it
<pb facs="tcp:2186:45"/> might be) al the commandements of God.</p>
            <p>But here it may be demaunded, how a den of ſo many ſuperſtitions can be called the Church,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.15</note> which ought to be the pillar of truth. I aunſweare, it is ſo called not that it retaineth all the qualities of the Church, but becauſe it hath ſome remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or remnant. Thus our ſauiour Chriſt called the Church a ſheepfold, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhepes ſake, notwithſtanding that the greater part were Lions, Beares, and Woolues. So <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> is called the holy Citie notwithſtanding that the greateſt parte were wicked. So the Church is called a corne feelde and yet the greateſt parte is chaffe, darnell, &amp; tares. In like manner, it is the temple of God, where the Pope ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, though it be defiled with an infinite number of ſacrileges.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shewing himſelfe that he is God.</hi> By theſe words the Apoſtle meaneth, that the pride of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhalbe ſo great, that exempting himſelfe from the number and order of ſeruants, and aſcending vp to the tribunall ſeate of God, he will take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to commaund, not by humane thoritie, but as it were by diuine power.
<pb facs="tcp:2186:45"/> 
               <hi>5 Remember ye not that when I was yet with you, I told you theſe thinges?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle putteth the <hi>Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> againe in minde of the doctrine which he deliuered vnto them, of the diſſipation of the Church to come. And this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth the doctrine, that they had heard the ſame aforetime from his mouth, leſt they might thinke that it was deuiſed for a time. And whereas he did ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh them ſo timely of the kingdome of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> &amp; of the ruine, and decay of the Church which ſhould be in time to come, when as yet there was no queſtion moued concerning theſe thinges, no doubt it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be a doctrine moſt profitable to be knowne. And in very deed ſo it falleth out. They to whom he ſpake were to ſee many things which troubled them: but when the poſteritie did behold a great part of thoſe which had profeſſed Chriſt &amp; his Goſpell, as men ſtricken with a wood fury, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte from godlineſſe, and to runne head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into diſtruction, what could they doe elſe but ſtagger and ſtand in doubt? But here was a braſen wall, that God had ſo appointed, becauſe the vnthankfulneſſe of
<pb facs="tcp:2186:46"/> men had deſerued ſuch vengeance. Here we may ſee how forgetfull men are, when their eternall ſaluation is in queſtion. We are alſo to obſerue and note the humanitie of Paul, who hauing iuſt cauſe to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, doth neuertheleſſe gentlely reprehend them. For this is a fatherly checke. As if he ſhould ſay, what doe you meane to ſuffer falſe teachers to trouble you, and to turne you away from beleeuing my prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching? Remember thoſe thinges which I told you beforehand, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, when I was yet with you in <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonica.</hi> For I intreated and diſputed of the Apoſtaſie and abhominations of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> and of the comming of the iudge Chriſt in glorie.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6 And now ye knowe what withhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, that he might be reuealed in his time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle in theſe wordes preuenteth an obiection which might haue beene made thus: What cauſe is there why we ſhould not beleeue that the aduerſarie of Chriſt doth now reigne, and is already come, when we ſee that al the Potentates of this world do by all manner of meanes
<pb facs="tcp:2186:46"/> gainſay and reſiſt the name of Chriſt and his doctrine? To this the Apoſtle aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweareth ye know what is the let, or cauſe of delay. Many vnderſtand this to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire: Becauſe as the Monarchie of <hi>Babylon</hi> was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne by the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſes:</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the <hi>Macedonians</hi> hauing vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the <hi>Perſians,</hi> enioyed the monarchie, and at the laſt the <hi>Macedonians</hi> were ſubdued by the <hi>Romanes:</hi> euen ſo <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt</hi> ſhall violently take vnto himſelfe the vacant Dominion and rule of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> Empier. Theſe thinges are moſt true as touching the hiſtorie: but yet the meaning of the Apoſtle was otherwiſe, namely, that the doctrine of the Goſpell ſhould haue paſſage from place to place, vntil ſuch tim as almoſt the whole world were made giltie of obſtinacie and maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wickednes. For there is no doubt but that the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> had heard this impediment, whatſoeuer it was, from Pauls mouth, afore time: for he putteth them in minde of thoſe thinges, which he had taught them afore time, when he was perſonally preſent. Very many as the
<pb facs="tcp:2186:47"/> forerunners of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> ſought dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently in the time of Paul, and of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtles to ouerthrowe the doctrine of the Goſpell with their lies, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueable ſleights; (euen as Saint Iohn writeth, that there were already many begunne to be <hi>Antichriſtes.</hi>) And yet notwithſtanding as yet <hi>Antichriſt</hi> was not fully reuealed. To whoſe full ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment, appertaine blaſphemies, ſharpe and cruell perſecutions, hereſies, and ſuch other like impieties. All which thinges when the Goſpell had been preached throughout the worlde were in due time reuealed. Paul therefore preached vnto the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the vniuerſal calling of the Gentils, that to all ſortes of men the grace of God was to be offered, that Chriſt wold make a paſſage for his Goſpell throughout all the worlde, to the ende the empietie of men might the more appeare, and be more plainely conuinced. Therefore this Impediment, let, and delay (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Paul ſpeaketh) was to be made, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Goſpell had ended his full courſe: becauſe the free calling vnto ſaluation
<pb facs="tcp:2186:47"/> ought to be firſt in order. Therefore he addeth:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In hys time.</hi> Becauſe vengeance was to follow and take place, when grace was reiected: as in very deed, it came to paſſe.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7 (For the miſterie of iniquitie doth already woorke: onely he which now withholdeth, ſhall let, till he be taken out of the way.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon why <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhall not be reuealed now, but in his time, is taken from the circumſtance of time, vntil which time <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhall raigne by Gods per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. Paul teacheth that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> hath at no time ceaſſed, but hath alwayes laboured to intangle and enſnare the Church of Chriſt, and hath alſo gone about in the very times of the Apoſtles to ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broch his practiſes of iniquitie. For as yet ſathan was not ſo ſtrong, that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> could openly aſſaile &amp; oppreſſe the Church: therefore priuilie and by ſtelth he ſought to doe that, which afterward in due time, he would doe openly. For then he did but lay the foundations ſecretly, vpon the which he might afterward reare his
<pb facs="tcp:2186:48"/> building: as it came to paſſe. And hereby that is more fullie confirmed, which we haue already ſaid, that no one man is noted vnder the name of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">This Phocas to aſpire to the Empire, killed his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Mauritius the Emperour: and then to make his ſeate more ſure, he graunted to Boniface 3. whatſoeuer he would, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him the ſupremacie, and name of vniuerſall Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ouer all Chriſtian Churches. Thus the firſt declining of the Church began in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no. Domi. 610. or there about</note> but one kingdome, which exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it ſelfe into many ages. For the defection hath continued openly to be ſeen of all men from the time of <hi>Phocas,</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Boniface</hi> the third, which was about the yeere of our Lorde <hi>610.</hi> vntill this day. Moreouer, although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle meaneth heere a ſecret working, yet notwithſtanding he rather vſeth the name of miſterie, then any other, alluding vnto the miſterie of ſaluation, of the which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans, Chapter 16.25.</hi> For he doth diligently note the conflicte of repugnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, betweene the ſonne of God, and the ſonne of perdition.</p>
            <p>Alſo this word <hi>miſterie</hi> teacheth, that it is no marueile if neither our prediceſſors nor we our ſelues vnderſtood the impietie of <hi>Antichriſt:</hi> becauſe it was a <hi>miſterie,</hi> and becauſe he ſecretly practiſed his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Onely he which now withholdeth
<pb facs="tcp:2186:48"/> ſhall let, till he be taken out of the way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words are without al doubt to be referred vnto <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> For the Apoſtle addeth this for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that the kingdome of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be temporall, to the which God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed an ende. For the faithfull might haue obiected, to what end is the Goſpell preached, if Sathan now beginneth that tiranny which ſhall alwayes indure? Therefore he exhorteth them to patience: becauſe God wil afflict his church but for a time onely, and will after that deliuer it againe: and on the contrary parte, the perpetuitie of Chriſtes kingdome is to be conſidered, that the faithfull may reſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame,</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8 And then ſhall the wicked man be reuealed, whom the Lorde ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume with the ſpirite of his mouth, and ſhall aboliſh with the brightneſſe of his comming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſheweth that the kingdome of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt</hi> ſhall not be alwayes a miſterie: that thereby the faithful may receiue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. For he ſhalbe reuealed, and
<pb facs="tcp:2186:49"/> ſhall ariſe manifeſtly he ſhalbe mightie, and ſhal bring to paſſe whatſoeuer he wil, both in the woorking of iniquitie, and alſo of error. But when ſhall that be? Euen then (ſaith he) when that let (whereof mention is made in the ſixt verſe) ſhalbe taken away. For the ſeuenth verſe is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in a <hi>parentheſis.</hi> So that he doth not appoint the time of reuelation, when <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is taken away (of which men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made in the ſeuenth verſe): but he hath reſpect vnto the ſixt verſe: where he had ſaid that there was a let which ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Antichriſt</hi> that he could not openly get poſſeſſion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome: afterward he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that he went about a priuie woorke of impietie. And thirdly he ioyneth hereunto in the ſeuenth verſe, a conſolation, that this tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny ſhal haue an end. Now againe here he repeateth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he which as yet is hidden, ſhalbe reuealed in his time: which repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion tendeth to this end, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the faithful be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing armed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpiritual weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, may fight neuertheleſſe couragiouſly vnder Chriſt, &amp; not ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to be drowned, what floud of impietie ſoeuer doth ouerflowe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The wicked man.</hi> The Greke worde <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifieth him which will be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect
<pb facs="tcp:2186:49"/> to no law, which neither careth for man, nor feareth God. As if the Apoſtle ſhould ſay, that lawles deceiuer, and moſt wicked man, which will not be holden within the liſtes of good and godly lawes, but ruſheth, headlong to the breath both of humane and diuine ordinances, and boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth himſelfe to be aboue al men, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning al manner of perſons, and al things, oppreſſing al mens libertie, &amp; not ſuffering himſelfe to be iudged of any, and requiring this eſpecially, that all men obey his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt conſtitutions, without any regard had of profite or of honeſtie <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whom the Lord ſhall conſume with the ſpirite of his mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now followeth the ruine and diſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ruine and fall of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</note> Paul hath ſpoken in the ſeuenth verſe going before, of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of this kingdome: now he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth the manner how it ſhalbe diſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, namely, it ſhalbe brought to nothing by the worde of the Lord. Notwithſtanding it may be, that he ſpeaketh of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Chriſt, when he ſhall come a iudge from heauen, for ſo the wordes may ſeeme to import. Howbeit Paul meaneth not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt wil do this thing in a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. For
<pb facs="tcp:2186:50"/> 
               <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhall not fall downe in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as wounded with one ſtroke, but after many aſſaults and battels, he ſhal at the laſt periſh. But he ſhal not be deſtroied with the hand of man, with the multitude of an hoaſt, with the valour and courage of ſouldiers, nor with the thunderclaps of Canon ſhot, but with the hand &amp; power of God. Therefore we muſt be well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhalbe vtterly aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and brought to naught, when that laſt day of reformation of all thinges ſhall come. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding Paul doth giue vs thus much to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that Chriſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his bright beames, which he will ſend foorth before his comming, will driue away the darkneſſe in the which <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhall raigne: euen as the Sunne, before it ſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnto vs, doth driue away the darknes of the night. Therefore this victorye of Gods worde ſhalbe in this world: for the ſpirite of his mouthe ſignifieth no other thing but his woorde: as alſo in <hi>Eſay,</hi> where it is ſaid, <hi>He ſhall ſmite the earth with the ſword of his mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 11.4.</note> 
               <hi>and with the breath of his lips, ſhall he ſlay the wicked:</hi> To the which place Paul
<pb facs="tcp:2186:50"/> ſeemeth to allude. For there the Prophet by the ſworde of his mouth, and breath of his lips vnderſtandeth al one thing, which weapons he giueth vnto Chriſt, therewith to diſtroy his enimies. For the worde of God is more ſharpe then any two edged ſworde, and it is that ſworde of might, which ſhall cut of the head off this proud <hi>Goliah.</hi> For <hi>Antichriſt</hi> pleadeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe of the moſt high, and ſaith that all his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and authoritie is grounded vpon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine lawes: vnder the pretence and colour wherof, he hath hetherto raigned in ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. But ſo ſoone as the light of the Goſpel began to ſhine, by &amp; by the darke cloudes of this deceiuer vaniſhed away. For it is manifeſt to all men (which will ſee) that this man of ſinne is cleane contrary to Chriſt, both in manners, and alſo in lawes. Therefore it is come to paſſe, that all which feare God, knowing his truth, do loath and abhor that <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and do forſake him. Wherefore the ſword that doth kill him is the worde of God. For then he is moſt euidently ſlaine, when his nature and diſpoſition is manifeſtly knowne by the doctrine of truth. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation
<pb facs="tcp:2186:51"/> and knowledge of him, doth wound him to the heart, and caſt him downe: and contrariwiſe the ignorance of him, doth aduance him. For they which know him not, do beleeue him to be an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall Prophet, and a God. Whereas they which haue truely knowne him, doe know him to be an <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> Therfore when the Apoſtle ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Lord wil kil <hi>Antichriſt</hi> with the breath of his mouth, he meaneth that he wil reueale, confound, and diſcouer him by his worde. The which is come to paſſe this day in ſomuch that his Lions ſkinne, being taken from him, little children do ſee his Aſſes eares, and he is made a ſcorne vnto men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſhall Aboliſh with the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his comming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle meaneth that ſuch ſhalbe the brightnes of Chriſt his countenance, that it ſhall ſwallowe vp the darkeneſſe of <hi>Antichriſt:</hi> withall he doth priuilie giue to vnderſtand that it is permitted vnto <hi>Antichriſt:</hi> to take his tourne &amp;, to inioy his kingdome for a ſeaſon, euen ſo long as it ſhal pleaſe Chriſt to withdraw himſelfe the which our ſauiour Chriſt hath done, by
<pb facs="tcp:2186:51"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aking from men his light, when he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eene that they haue abuſed the ſame. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f we like better to vnderſtand the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le as ſpeaking of the laſt appearing of Chriſt, then it ſeemeth that he doth allude <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the woordes of the Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 7.11.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here he ſaith, <hi>The iudgment was ſet, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he bookes opened. Then I beheld, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en till the beaſt was ſlaine, and his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y deſtroyed and giuen to the burning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re, &amp;c.</hi> And therefore Paul ſaith here, <hi>Whom he ſhall aboliſh with the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſe of his comming.</hi> For the Lord ſaith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Goſpell:<note place="margin">Mat. 24.27.</note> 
               <hi>As the lightning com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth out of the Eaſt, &amp; goeth into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt, So ſhall the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of the ſonne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f man be: for he ſhall come in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouds of heauen, with power &amp; great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>orie.</hi> Therfore this opinion is falſe, that kingdome of impiety ſhal vtterly fal and euer appeare againe, at the time of reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tion, wherof the Apoſtle hath ſpoken hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>erto: or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhal be aboliſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day of iudgment, by martial force &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight. But rather this battaile betweene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hriſt and <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhal continue to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. Neuertheles Chriſt at his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ming, ſhal vtterly deface &amp; raſe him out
<pb facs="tcp:2186:52"/> for euer. In the meane time, it is certain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> true, at the time when <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uealed, a great number of men ſhall fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſake him, as we ſee it is come to paſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this age. For although he, preſuming vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on the force of war, doth ſpoile &amp; oppreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſaints of the moſt high, yet the mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt do withſtand him, and do ſtrike him with the ſworde of Gods word pull of his viſor, accuſe his impietie, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo at the laſt do kill him. For in the heart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of theſe men he is ſlaine, and his author<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie defaced. But though he be ouer come he will furiouſly rage ſtill, vntill t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be vtterly aboliſhed by the iudge Chriſt, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whom alone this victorie is reſerued. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the meane time euery one of vs mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> watch vigilantly, that he hurte none of v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as afore time he hath done: for therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the worde of God hath detected him vnt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vs, that we might ſhunne and beware <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his peſtilent ſnares.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9 Euen him whoſe comming is b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the woorking of Sathan, with all po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer and ſignes, and lying woonders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto the Apoſtle hath intreated the kingdome, reuelation, and ruine
<pb facs="tcp:2186:52"/> 
               <hi>Antichriſt:</hi> and now returning to him backe againe, he doth deſcribe more at large his power and woorkes. And he confirmeth the ſentence going afore, with an argument of the contraries. For ſeeing that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> doth not ſtand without the ſubtill deceits of Sathan, ſo ſoone as Chriſt doth ſhine, he muſt needes vaniſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Furthermore, becauſe he raigneth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n darkneſſe only, the day ariſing, his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is extinguiſhed. Therefore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tle teacheth that it ſhalbe a moſt eaſie thing for Chriſt to diſtroy the kingdome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd tiranny of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> which is vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olden with no other thing, then with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eceiueable ſleights of Sathan. Yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ertheleſſe, he addeth certaine notes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hereby that ſonne of perdition may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly be diſcerned. In this deſcription he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttributeth vnto him Sathan for his rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r and guide, by whom <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhalbe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade able to deceiue others: leſt the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll might thinke that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> impotent, or his kingdome weake. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow, the power and woorkings of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an doe conſiſt in murther and in lies, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hriſt witneſſeth, ſaying. <hi>He was a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer
<pb facs="tcp:2186:53"/> from the beginning and aboad not in the trueth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 8.44.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe there is no truth in him. When he ſpeaketh of a lie, he ſpeaketh of his owne, becauſe he is a lyar, and the father of the ſame thing.</hi> And Paul in this preſent place, expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by repitition the working of Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, reckoneth vp, power and ſignes, that is to ſay, monſtrous lyes, and the deceiueable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of vnrighteouſneſſe. And in very deed that this kingdome might be quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the kingdome of Chriſt, it was neceſſarie that it ſhould conſiſt partly in falſe doctrine and in errors, and partly in falſe and fayned miracles. For the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt doth ſtand vpon the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of truth, and on the power of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite. Therefore Sathan to oppoſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the perſon of his vicar againſt Chriſt, hath put on the name and viſor of Chriſt: and yet notwithſtanding withall, he hath choſen ſuch weapons as where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he may directly oppugne Chriſt. Chriſt with the doctrine of his Goſpell doth illuminate our mindes vnto euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life: <hi>Antichriſt</hi> being taught and inſtructed by Sathan, with wicked &amp; falſe
<pb facs="tcp:2186:53"/> doctrine draweth the wicked to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Chriſt ſhewed foorth the power of his ſpirite, confirming the Goſpell with mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles to ſaue mens ſoules: the aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, by the efficacie of Sathan, doth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw vs from the holy ghoſt, and with his falſehoodes and ſleightes, confirmeth mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable men in error. As touching ſignes wicked <hi>Mahomet,</hi> was woont to ſay,<note place="margin">Mahomet came not with miracles but with force.</note> that he came not in the power of ſignes, but in martiall force, whereby he manifeſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that for the ſetting vp of his new law, he did nothing elſe, but play the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked murtherer. The wicked lying man and tyrannicall deceiuer ſawe that the Goſpell of Chriſt had proper teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of diuine power by miraculous ſignes, the which when he wanted, he determined to bring all thinges to paſſe, by cruell violence. In the papacie great boaſt hath beene made of miracles the which manifeſtly appearing to bee contrary to the worde, and doctrine of the Goſpell, do plainly appeare to come out of the ſhoppe of Sathan. The Apoſtle cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them lying wonders, not onely which
<pb facs="tcp:2186:54"/> are lyingly and falſely fayned, of craftie men to deceiue the ſimple (with the which y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> papacie doth woonderfully abound): but alſo he placeth the lie &amp; falſehood herein, that Sathan doth abuſe thoſe miracles, which otherwiſe are the very workes of God, and draweth them to a contrarie ende, to obſcure the glorie of God. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding there is no doubt but that he doth deceiue by illuſions:<note place="margin">Exod. 11.</note> example whereof we haue in <hi>Pharaos</hi> Magicians.</p>
            <p>Therfore, there are two ſorts of ſignes: true, and falſe. Thoſe are true ſignes, which offer the very thinges, without any fantaſie. Such are all the ſignes of the Prophets, of the Apoſtles, of Moſes and of Chriſt. They are falſe ſignes, which by the ſufferance of God, are done either by Sathan himſelfe, or by his miniſters, to the derogation of the truth, and confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that which is falſe. Of theſe falſe ſignes there are diuers kindes. Some there are which beguile men vnder a falſe forme: and there are ſome, which truely appeare as they are in deede, but to this ende, to ſeduce men from truth to falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. Concerning theſe ſignes reade the
<pb facs="tcp:2186:54"/> 
               <hi>24.</hi> of Mathewe.<note place="margin">Mat. 24.24.</note> Verely the eſtimation of popiſhe religion increaced by nothing more, then by the often vſe of miracles. By miracles Tranſubſtantiation, prayer to ſaintes, and woorſhipping of images got credit with the worlde. For no man is able to rehearſe the woonderfull ſleightes of legerdemaine, with the which Sathan hath beguiled the whole worlde: in ſome place forſooth hogs worſhipped y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread of the pix. At another time the bread left his forme: and a little boy appeared: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, a pece of fleſh: Yea and that which is more monſtrous, great ſtreames of bloud were ſeene to runne from the ſame. What will you ſay, if images did goe, or if they were ſent by God from heauen: if ſuch as were hid were reuealed: if ſome laughed and wept: if other ſome ſent gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering and ſhining beames wonderfully from them: if ſome grewe and increaſed in bigneſſe: if other ſome vaniſhed away: yea if many of them often times ſpake? Of theſe thinges it was not lawfull for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man to doubt: nay, it was death not to worſhippe theſe impieties, and not to receiue them as come from God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:2186:55" rendition="simple:additions"/> and appointed to be woorſhiped.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10 And in all deceiueablenes of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe among them that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe, becauſe they receiued not the loue of the truth, that they might be ſaued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe wordes Paul doth more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expound himſelfe concerning the cauſes of lying wonders: howbeit this may be referred to the comming of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhal come in al deceitfulneſſe of vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. That is to ſay, when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, he ſhall bring with him all manner of iniquities, by which he ſhall ſeduce men from that which is true, honeſt, and iuſt, and ſhall wrap them in hipocriſie and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors.</p>
            <p>For by the name of ſeduction which in Greke is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, fraud and deceit is ſignified, by which a man is ſeduced from the right way, not becauſe he which goeth aſtray goeth out of the way through his owne fault, but being deceiued with the fraud and ſubteltie of another, leſt he ſhould walke in the right way: euen as
<pb facs="tcp:2186:55"/> when we do beleeue and obey thoſe, which do turne vs away from the faith in Chriſt, and from true repentance toward God, being perſwaded that they teach vs thoſe thinges which are true and right. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſay, that by the working of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> common iuſtice, all honeſtie, and ſincere trueth ſhalbe remoued from their place, and in ſteede thereof, vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, hypocriſie, impudencie, luſt, and moſt vaine perſwaſion, ſubſtituted. The which thinges, who ſeeth not that they haue poſſeſſed all ſortes and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men at this day, but ſuch as wil ſee nothing?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In them that periſhe.</hi> He doth limitte the power of Sathan, leſt ſome ſhould thinke, that he could hurte Gods elect:<note place="margin">Mat. 24. ver. 24.</note> euen as our ſauiour Chriſt alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empteth them from this peril. Wherby it doth appeare that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> doth not preuaile ſo farre as he doth, but by Gods ſufferance. Neither were all ſeduced by <hi>Antichriſt:</hi> nay rather many good Chriſtians, in the very kingdome of darknes and blindnes, and of all iniquitie,
<pb facs="tcp:2186:56"/> were by the grace and goodneſſe of God ſaued, as <hi>Iohn Hus, Hierome of Prage,</hi> and many others, as ſhall appeare to them which reade eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories. The which is therefore to be noted, leaſt any man ſhould thinke that there ceaſed to be a Church vnder the kingdome of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt:</hi> but we muſt beleeue that alwayes from the beginning of the world, God hath had his Church, one while greater, &amp; another while leſſe. This therfore was a neceſſarie conſolation. For otherwiſe the godly muſt needes haue beene diſcouraged through feare, if they ſhould ſee no way for them to goe, but into a gaping and deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring gulphe. Therfore Paul, as he would haue vs to be carefull, to looke vnto our ſelues, leſt by too much ſecuritie we come vnto diſtruction: ſo he commaundeth vs to hope wel, becauſe the power of Sathan is reſtrayned and brideled, that he cannot bring to ruine other then reprobates. For thoſe cannot be ſeduced whom Chriſt hath in his hand,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ohn. 10.8.</note> becauſe he is a faithfull and mightie preſeruer of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Becauſe they receiued not the loue of the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2186:56"/>
            <p>Leaſt the reprobate might complaine, that they periſh giltleſſe, and that they are appointed to diſtruction rather through cruelty in God, then for their own offence: Paul ſheweth for what iuſt cauſes ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere vengeance of God ſhall come vpon them, namely, becauſe they haue not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced the truth offered to them, with ſuch affection as became them: but haue rather willingly reiected their ſaluation. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their obſtinate rebellion againſt Chriſt deſerueth, that they which haue not receiued Chriſt, deſiring through his great loue to ſaue all men, and for his truethes ſake reuealing thoſe thinges which pertaine to ſaluation, that they might be ſaued: now by the permiſſion of God, falſehood may preuaile with them in ſteede of trueth, tyranny for charitie, a deſtroyer for a Sauiour, and that now they may beleeue the lies of wicked men, which refuſed to beleeue the ſonne of God preaching the trueth. And hereby that which we haue already ſaid doth more plainely appeare, that it was expedient for the Goſpel to be preached to the world, before God gaue ſo great ſcope and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="tcp:2186:57"/> vnto Sathan: becauſe God would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue ſuffered ſo foule a prophanation of his temple, if he had not beene prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thereunto with the extreeme vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of men. To be breefe, Paul teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhalbe a miniſter of Gods iuſt vengeance againſt thoſe, which being called to ſaluation, haue reiected the Goſpell, and haue rather giuen ouer their mindes to impietie and errors. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the papiſtes haue now no colour to make this obiection, that it became not the clemencie of Chriſt thus to caſt off his Church. For although <hi>Antichriſt</hi> raigned like a tirant, yet none periſhed but they which were worthy, and which willingly ſought their owne death. And in very deed, when as the voice of Chriſt did ſound eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, the eares of men were deafe and willfully ſtopt againſt the ſame: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the profeſſion of Chriſtianiſme was very common, very few notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding did truely and with their whole heart giue themſelues vnto Chriſt. Therefore it is no marueile, if vpon ſuch wicked con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempte, there enſued vengeance accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2186:57"/>
            <p>The loue of the trueth, is the loue, ſtudy, and earneſt deſire of the trueth, eſpecially of that doctrine, which is deliuered in the Goſpel, concerning our eternall ſaluation through Chriſte. This trueth the Papiſts doe impugne with no leſſe crueltie, then they haue alwayes done the profeſſours thereof.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11 And therefore God ſhall ſende them ſtrong deluſion, that they ſhould beleeue lyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle ſtil proceedeth with the puniſhment of incredulitie and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitencie, by which two vices it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe that ſome doe ſpeake againſt the doctrine of truth &amp; ſaluation. He doth not onely ſay, that men ſhall beleue errors, but alſo that the reprobate ſhall be blinded in ſuch wiſe, that without all iudgement they ſhall runne headlong into death. For as God doth inwardly illuminate vs with his ſpirite, that his doctrine may be effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall with vs, and doth open our eyes and heartes, that it may pierce and enter ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, euen ſo by his iuſt iudgement hee deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth thoſe ouer into a reprobate ſence, whom hee hath appointed to deſtruction,
<pb facs="tcp:2186:58"/> that with cloſed eyes and dulled minds, as men voyde of ſence &amp; aſtoniſhed, they may yeelde them ſelues to Sathan and to his miniſters, to be deceiued. And being ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, they are moſt perilouſly beguiled: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when they doe beleeue that they are in the way of righteouſneſſe, of trueth, and of ſaluation, they doe walke in the waye of iniquity, of lies, and of euerlaſting deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And in very deed we haue a manifeſt ſpectacle of this thing in the papacie. It cannot be told what a woonderfull heape of errors are therin, what groſſe and ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full abſurdity of ſuperſtitions, and what doting diluſions and dreames, farre from common ſence. All they which haue but a meane taſt of the ſacred Scriptures, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſomuch as thinke of thoſe monſtrous thinges without great horror. How com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it to paſſe then that all the world is aſtoniſhed in ſuch wiſe that they cannot ſee them, but becauſe the Lorde hath ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them with blindneſſe, &amp; turned them as it were into ſenceleſſe blockes? For de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueable ſleights are effectuall in them, becauſe the Diuell worketh together in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, blinding the minds of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnbeleeuing,
<pb facs="tcp:2186:58"/> that the light of the glory of the Goſpell which is the image of God,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.</note> might not ſhine vnto them. Therefore we muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and note in this place that impietie, lyes, errors, ſectes, and hereſies, with ſuch like, are puniſhments of the contempt of Gods worde. For God is not wont to ſuffer the contempt of his worde to eſcape vnpuniſhed: but doth moſt grieuouſly take vengeance on the ſame: that men may knowe that there is no dallying with God. So our aunceſtors were puniſhed with deceiueable wayes in the myſt of darkeneſſe, for the contempt of the word, becauſe they beleeued lyes. Now we may eaſily gather by examples already paſt, what is to be feared will befall vs vnthankfull men at this day, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Goſpell of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12 That all they might be iudged which beleeue not the truth, but haue approued vnrighteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is to ſay, that they might ſuffer the puniſhment due for their impietie, and periſh by the iuſt iudgment of God. So that there is no cauſe why they that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe ſhould any manner of way laye the
<pb facs="tcp:2186:59"/> blame vpon God: becauſe they haue got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that which they ſought for. For we muſt remember what <hi>Moſes</hi> writeth, that our heartes are tried and proued, when falſe doctrines are publiſhed by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers: becauſe they doe not preuaile with any but with thoſe which doe not loue God w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their whole heart.<note place="margin">Deut. 13.3.</note> Therfore they which loue vnrighteouſnes ſhal reape the fruite thereof. So Chriſt ſaid vnto the Iewes:<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.40.</note> 
               <hi>But ye wil not come to me that ye might haue life. I receiue not prayſe of men. But I knowe you, that ye haue not the loue of God in you. I am come in my fathers name, and ye receiue me not: If another ſhall come in his owne name, him will ye receiue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Apoſtle ſaith here, <hi>That al,</hi> he giueth vs to vnderſtand that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of God is not excuſed, by their great rout and multitude, which refuſe to obey the Goſpell. For God is a iudge of the whole world, who will as ſoone take vengeance vpon a hundred thouſand, as vpon one man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But haue approued vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> He expoundeth by an <hi>Antitheſis</hi> or
<pb facs="tcp:2186:59"/> compariſon, what it is, not to beleeue the truth. And the Greeke participle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifieth a willing promptneſſe vnto euill: and therefore it is tranſlated of ſome: <hi>But had pleaſure in vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes.</hi> Hereby all excuſe is taken from the vnthankeful, ſeeing they take ſo great pleaſure in vnrighteouſneſſe, that they prefer the ſame, before the righteouſneſſe of God. Now, if we doe compare with theſe woordes, thoſe things, which ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and the ſeduced Papiſtes, doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to be their great prayſe, we ſhall eaſily ſee, what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefe reward, which is due to them, namely, moſt fearefull wrath, and double condemnation. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or they will not beleeue the truth, but d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in vnrighteouſneſſe, and in impietie, being ſeduſed by the prince of da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>es, and by Sathan the father of lyes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s far concerning the crueltie and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ie of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> &amp; concerning of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euils which he hath brought into the Church by wicked doctrines, and by the oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Goſpell of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <hi>13 But we ought alwayes to giue thankes to God for you, brethren, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued
<pb facs="tcp:2186:60"/> of the Lorde, becauſe that God hath from the beginning choſen you to ſaluation, through ſanctification of the ſpirit, and the faith of truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle hauing before declared certaine horrible thinges, which might terrefie and trouble the hearers minde, doth now comfort the heartes of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and doth more plainely ſegregate, &amp; diſſeuer the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, leaſt their faith might wauer with the feare of the defectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to come. Howbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it his intention was to prouide not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for them: but alſo for poſterities to come: neither doth he only confirme them that they might not be carried into the ſame ruine with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world: but alſo by this c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pariſon, he doth the more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of God towards the: that whereas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> behold almoſt the whole world to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed headlong together, as it were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iolent empeſt, they by the hand o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> liued in a quiet and firme ſtate of l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fe. Thus it is conuenient to behold the i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ments of God in the reprobate, that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may be as it were looking glaſſes vnto vs, to conſider his mercie toward vs.
<pb facs="tcp:2186:60"/> For we muſt make this accoumpt, that it commeth to paſſe onely by the ſingular grace and fauour of God, that we in like manner doe not periſhe miſerably with them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brethren beloued of the Lorde.</hi> He calleth them ſo, that they may the better conſider that they are for no other cauſe deliuered from the vniuerſall diſtruction of the worlde, but becauſe God hath free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loued them. Of this fauour and grace of God, <hi>Moſes</hi> remembred the Iewes, ſaying:<note place="margin">Deut. 7.7.</note> 
               <hi>God hath not therefore ſo greatly exalted you, becauſe you were more mightie, or mo in number than others but becauſe he loued your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> For ſo often as we heare mention made of his loue, we ought by and by to remember that ſaying of the Apoſtle, <hi>Not that we loued him firſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 4.10.</note> And the certaine and ſure ſignes of the loue of God toward vs, are the proclayming of the Goſpell, and the preaching of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes through Chriſt. For by that publication of Gods will, it is both teſtified that we are receiued into the grace of adoption through Chriſt, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb facs="tcp:2186:61"/> are reckoned in the number of Gods ſonnes, if ſo be we receiue the doctrine of the Goſpell through faith, and doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our ſelues to the grace of the moſt mercifull God.<note place="margin">Pſal. 147.11. Iohn. 3.16.</note> For the Lord loueth thoſe that feare him, and that put their truſt in his mercie. Moreouer God ſo loued the worlde that he gaue his onely begotten ſonne,<note place="margin">Ephe. 16.</note> that they that beleue in him ſhould not periſh but haue euerlaſting life. This therefore is that grace of God, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs accepted through the beloued, that is, through Chriſt. Wo therefore be vnto thoſe wicked teachers, which wil haue vs to doubte of the Grace of God, and whether we are loued of God, when as God would haue vs, more ſure of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, then that beleeuing the Goſpell, we aſſure our ſelues to be in his fauour, and to be beloued of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Becauſe that God hath from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning choſen you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle expreſſeth the cauſe, why all men ſhal not be ouerwhelmed in one and the ſelfe ſame deſtruction: namely becauſe Sathan can doe nothing againſt thoſe to hinder their ſaluation, although heauen and earth be confounded toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb facs="tcp:2186:61"/> For this ſaying of Chriſt ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes abide moſt firme. <hi>My ſheepe hear my voice and I knowe them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 10.27.</note> 
               <hi>and they follow me: and I giue vnto them eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, neither ſhall they periſh for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and no man ſhall take them ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> my hande.</hi> There is no doubt, but tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of Gods eternall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: For he meaneth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is no feare of the altering of their ſaluation, which is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpon gods eternal election, thogh there happen a troubleſome alteration of thinges. As if he ſhould ſay, let this be a horror and feare to others, to thoſe (I ſay) which periſh, &amp; in whom the Diuels can much preuaile: but as for you, ye are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out peril, as the beloued of God, &amp; ſuch as are elected fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning. Therefore what garboyle &amp; trouble ſoeuer Sathan woorketh in the worlde, yet your ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was laid vp in ſafety for you, before the world was made. For election ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a purpoſe of ſhewing mercie, and of ſauing thoſe, whom God hath ordayned by that purpoſe, to obtayne eternall life for an inheritance. But becauſe it is not our part to enter into the ſecret counſell of God, there to ſeeke the certaintie of
<pb facs="tcp:2186:62"/> our ſaluation, he deliuereth vnto vs cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſignes and tokens of election, which ought ſufficiently to aſſure vs thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Through ſanctification of the ſpirit.</hi> That is to ſay by the holy Ghoſt, which doth purifie our hearts, and giue vnto vs a true faith. Therefore to know whether God hath elected vs or no, we muſt not ſeeke what God hath done before the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde: but we ſhal finde in our ſelues a lawfull triall, namely if he hath ſanctified vs with his ſpirit, &amp; eſtabliſhed vs in the faith of his Goſpell. For it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office of the holy Ghoſt, to illuminate our darkened heartes, which are naturally blinde, to teach the ignorant, to comfort the afflicted, to bringe thoſe that goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray into the right way, and ſo to ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them, that their workes may be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the omnipotent God. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle calleth that the <hi>Faith of truth,</hi> by which the elect doe beleeue the Goſpell of Chriſt. For this is contrary to that falſe perſwaſion, concerning the which Iames pronounceth, ſaying: <hi>Faith without workes is dead</hi> And the faith which we heare to the Goſpell,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mes. 2.</note> is an aſſured teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb facs="tcp:2186:62"/> of our adoption: and the ſpirit doth giue that adoption: and they which are led by the ſpirit of God,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.14. Iohn. 3.36.</note> are the ſonnes of God. And he which poſſeſſeth Chriſt by faith, hath euerlaſting life. All which thinges are diligently to be noted, leaſt we pretermitting the reuelation of Gods will, whereupon he commaundeth vs to reſt, we going about to drawe the ſame from his ſecrete counſell, in the which he woulde not haue vs inquiſitiue, ſhould bring our ſelues into a confuſed laberinth or maze. Therefore we muſt holde our ſelues contented, with the faith of the Goſpell, and with the grace of the ſpirit, by which we are regenerated, that we may aſſure our ſelues to be elected of God, and that we ſhall haue the ſaluation of eternall life, if we doe truly beleeue in Chriſt, the ſonne of God. And hereby their wickednes is confuted, which make Gods election a cloake of all filthyneſſe, when as Peter ſo ioyneth the ſame with faith and regeneration,<note place="margin">1. Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that they cannot be ſeparated. And Paul himſelfe in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place teſtifieth,<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.4.</note> that we were elected before the foundation of the world
<pb facs="tcp:2186:63"/> was layed, that we might be blameleſſe and holy in the ſight of God, in loue.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <hi>14 Whereunto he called you by our Goſpell, to obtaine the glorie of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The preaching of the Goſpell pertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> confirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of election. For this is the meane by which we come vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, whereunto God hath choſen vs. God therefore hath called vs vnto a true faith, not by the righteouſnes of the law, but by the Goſpell: euen as Paul teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in an other place,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>He hath ſaued and called vs, with an holy calling, not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our works, but according to his owne purpoſe and grace, which was giuen to vs through Chriſt Ieſus, before the world was, but is now made manifeſt by the appearing of our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus Chriſt, who hath aboliſhed death, and hath brought life and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie vnto light, through the Goſpell.</hi> And therefore, by the Goſpell, becauſe no man can beleeue in Chriſt, but by the publication therof, who being now glorified raigneth at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right hand of God the father in heauen.<note place="margin">Rom. 10.17</note> For faith commeth
<pb facs="tcp:2186:63"/> by hearing, and hearing by the worde of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By our Goſpell.</hi> He calleth it his Goſpell, not that it ſprang from him, but becauſe the preaching thereof was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him. As if he ſhould ſay: By the Goſpell which we haue preached, which was committed to vs to preach. And here are to be noted certaine degrees of our ſaluation. For we are from the beginning choſen to ſaluation: and then we are made partakers of ſaluation through ſanctification of the ſpirite, through beleeuing of the truth, and through the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To obtaine the glorie of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This doth bring no ſmall conſolation to the faithful, when they know that doth they and their ſaluation are ſo in the handes of God, euen as a fixed and firme inheritance is in the power of ſome Lord. To this ende pertaine theſe places,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Aſke of me, and I will giue thee the heathen for thyne inheritance, and the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt partes of the earth for thy poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> Againe,<note place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt hath purchaſed a
<pb facs="tcp:2186:64"/> Church to himſelfe by his blood.</hi> For God hath called vs, that we might be a glorious and peculiar people, of Ieſus Chriſt, a holy nation, innocent, &amp; immacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, which might honor and worſhippe God, and that God himſelfe might dwell in the heartes of thoſe that worſhip him. The which ought to allure vs to holineſſe of life. For God hath not called vs to luſt and vncleanneſſe, but vnto holineſſe and ſinceritie, and that we might be his holy temple.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <hi>15 Therefore brethren ſtand faſt, and keepe the inſtructions, which ye haue beene taught, either by word, or by our Epiſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the concluſion in tho which the Apoſtle requireth perſeuerance, both of faith, and alſo of manners, or of good workes.</p>
            <p>And therefore he bringeth in this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation very aptly vpon the premiſſes, becauſe our conſtancie, and power of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuering doth leane vpon the truſt and confidence of Gods grace. For when God doth call vs to ſaluation, by reaching foorth as it were his hand vnto vs: when
<pb facs="tcp:2186:64"/> Chriſt doth offer vs to inioy and poſſeſſe him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lfe, by the doctrine of the Goſpell, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the holy Ghoſt is giuen vnto vs as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and pledge of eternall life, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though heauen ſhould fall, we ought not to fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or be diſcouraged. For he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> to ſtand faſt, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t onely when others doe ſtand: but alſo when they ſaw almoſt all men to fall away from the faith, and all thinges to be full of confuſion, to abide neuertheleſſe then in their ſtate. And in very deede the calling wherewith God doth call vs, ought ſo to arme and confirme vs againſt all offences, that the vniuerſall ruine of the world, ſhould not ſhake our firmenes. For we muſt ſtand like ſouldiers which are placed in their aray, to fight againſt the enimies of Criſtianiſme. For con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie, and the power of perſeuering is neceſſary for vs, without the which it ſhal profite nothing, that we haue once begun well in the exerciſes of Godlineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And kepe the inſtructions which ye haue beene taught.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are ſome which reſtrayne theſe wordes vnto the ordinances of ciuill go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerment,
<pb facs="tcp:2186:65"/> amiſſe: for he ſheweth the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of ſtanding faſt. But it is a matter of greater importance, then externall d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline. Paul therefore calleth all hoſe thinges inſtructions, which by hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> had lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed, that is to ſay, the doctrine of the Goſpell, concerning true repentance towardes God, and concerning true faith in the Lorde Ieſus. For it was not lawfull for the Apoſtle of Ieſus Chriſt to teach any other thing. And the writings of Paul do ſufficiently ſhew what matter he did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially teach, and how he is to be imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Godly teachers of the Church. For he followed that order of teaching which Chriſt deliuered vnto him, being neither inferior, nor contrary to any other Apoſtle in doctrine. The Papiſtes doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe this place for the defence of mens traditions. And they frame their reaſon thus: if it was lawfull for Paul to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund traditions, it is alſo lawfull for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther teachers to doe it likewiſe: and if it were a Godly thing to obſerue them, then is it meet, that theſe be no leſſe obſerued. But admitte that Paul ſpake of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts
<pb facs="tcp:2186:65"/> which appertained to the externall gouernment of the Church, yet we ſay that they were not made, or ordayned by him, but commaunded of the Lord. For in another place he teſtifieth that it is not his purpoſe to inſnare the conſciences of men: euen as it was not lawfull for him,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.35.</note> nor for any of the Apoſtles to doe it: So that we doe acknowledge that we ought to receiue the Apoſtolicall traditions, euen as well as the written Epiſtles: but yet we doe not acknowledge that all they are Apoſtolicall traditions, which thoſe men thruſt vnto vs vnder the title of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall. Therefore they ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues very vndiſcrete, in going about to defend the filthy heape of their ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, vnder this title, as if they were the traditions of Paul. But the traditions of Paul are not contrary to his written E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles, as the traditions of theſe men are contrary vnto the writinges of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. But we will leaue thoſe trifling toyes, ſeeing we haue the ſincere meaning of Paul. And it may be iudged partly by the Epiſtle, what manner of traditions they be, which he commendeth. For he
<pb facs="tcp:2186:66"/> ſaith, <hi>Either by word:</hi> That is, my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, my preaching, or preſent inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Either by Epiſtle.</hi> What doth that contayne but pure doctrine, which doth vtterly ouerthrow all Popery, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fayned thinges, which are contrary to the ſimplicitie of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p n="16">
               <hi>16 Now the ſame Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, and our God, euen the father which hath loued vs, and hath giuen vs euerlaſting conſolation, and good hope through grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle hauing exhorted the <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians,</hi> doth now, according to his manner bleſſe them, and pray for them: thereby to make them more firme and ſtrong. Teaching thereby that all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian vertues, and perſeuerance therein, are giuen vnto vs of God: and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we haue need daily to pray vnto God for the ſame gifts, Therefore by this prayer he doth preuent the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> of a doubt, that they might not be carefull where to get ſtrength conſtanly to abide in ſincere doctrine. Neither is it negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to be pretermitted, that Paul te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth that our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt is
<pb facs="tcp:2186:66"/> the giuer of thoſe gifts with God our father. For thereby he giueth vs to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that he is God, and that he doth bring to paſſe with God the father that we do profite, and perſeuere in euery good worke. And he doth withall admoniſh vs that we cannot otherwiſe obtaine any thing from God, then by ſeeking the ſame in Chriſt himſelfe. Alſo for ſo much as he prayeth that God would giue vnto them thoſe thinges which he had commaunded, he thereby ſheweth, how little exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons doe preuaile, except God doe inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moue mens hearts. Verely mens eares ſhould heare onely a vaine ſound, if ſo be the holy Ghoſt ſhould not make the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine effectuall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And our God the father which hath loued vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Euen when we were enimies: how much more ſhall he loue vs,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.10.</note> now that we are reconciled through Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne. This the Apoſtle addeth to make the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> the more aſſured, that God would giue vnto them thoſe thinges which he prayed for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And hath giuen vs euerlaſting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2186:67"/>
            <p>This eternall conſolation, which he wil haue alway to remaine in his church, is the doctrine of the Goſpell, &amp; the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinne through Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And good hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The name of euerlaſting conſolation, and of good hope, tendeth to this end, that the faithfull may aſſuredly looke for an euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting continuance of gifts. He addeth, <hi>Through grace,</hi> to exclude mans merits, for the giftes of the holy Ghoſt are giuen vnto vs, through the free grace of God only, of the which we ſpeake the more often, that no man might proudly boaſt him ſelfe of the merits of his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.<note place="margin">Cor. 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>For what haſt thou,</hi> ſaith Paul, <hi>which thou haſt not receiued?</hi> Moreouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle hath very artificially comprehended the whole ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell in this verſe: namely, that God hath loued mankinde, and hath giuen euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting conſolation vnto him, Ieſus Chriſt, who is our hope: and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath giuen it him through his grace, and not for our merit, that we liue for euer. But what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles petition? it followeth.</p>
            <p n="17">
               <pb facs="tcp:2186:67"/>
               <hi>17. Comfort your heartes, and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhe you in euery worde, and good worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He prayeth for the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> that God ſo gentle and louing a father, would ſuſtaine and comfort their heartes with his conſolation, againſt all ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocks and offences, by which they might be brought into doubt and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire. For it belongeth vnto him to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte and ſtrengthen the heartes of his faithfull ſeruantes, that they might not faint through carefulneſſe or diſtruſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſtabliſh you in euery worde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then he prayeth that God would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme them in holſome doctrine. For this is the worde whereof he ſpeaketh, and not of any common worde: that it may agree with that which went before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And good worke.</hi> This partey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to the whole courſe of a good and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life, wherein the faithfull ought to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuere. Wherefore all the duties of a Chriſtian man, are comprehended in theſe two partes, namely, that they doe abide as well in holeſome doctrine, as in good manners of life. The which they
<pb facs="tcp:2186:68"/> cannot performe without the grace and helpe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Who ſaith:<note place="margin">Iohn. 15.5.</note> 
               <hi>Without me ye can doe nothing.</hi> That is to ſay, without my power and ſtrength working in you. And in another place it is ſaid, that we are framed by Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt vnto good workes,<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.10.</note> which God hath prepared that we ſhould walke in them. Theſe therefore are thoſe good fruites which doe ſpring from a ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed breſt, through the holy Ghoſt, and a true faith,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.6</note> without the which it is not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to pleaſe God. Finally Saint Paul hath ſo tempered this his prayer that withall he hath preſcribed what becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> namely, that they giue themſelues continually to all good words, and good works, &amp; that they doe perſeuere in euery good worke, but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially that they do acknowledge Chriſt to be the onely hope, and euerlaſting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of all the faithfull for euer.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:2186:68"/>
            <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>FVrthermore brethren, pray for vs,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>the word of the Lord may haue free paſſage, and be glorified euen as it is with you</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>This is the laſt part of this Epiſtle which comprehendeth foure exhortations: of the which, one is, the ſupplication of the Church, the which is very neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and profitable. For although the Lord was mightily preſent with the Apoſtle, and that he did exceed al others in the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uencie of prayer, yet neuertheleſſe he doth not neglect the prayer of the faithfull, with the which the Lorde will haue vs holpen. We in like manner after his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, ought alwayes to require this helpe, and to ſtirre vp the faithfull to pray for vs. For there is nothing more auaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with God then faithfull prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the worde of the Lord may haue free paſſage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For two cauſes the prayer of the Church is here required of the Apoſtle. The firſt is, for the happie ſucceſſe of the Goſpel, that the ſame being preached to other nations, might be no leſſe eſtemed
<pb facs="tcp:2186:69"/> then it was of the <hi>Theſſalonians.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by theſe wordes Paul ſheweth that he hath not ſo much care and conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of him ſelfe, as he hath of the whole Church. For why doth he deſire to be commended to the prayer of the <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians?</hi> That the doctrine of the Goſpel might haue his courſe. Therefore he would haue them to haue reſpect not ſo much to him alone, as to the glorie of Chriſt, and the common ſaluation of the Church. And the worde of the Lord is ſaid to haue free paſſage, when in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and in doctrine, it hath no let, but happie ſucceſſe, inſomuch y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many beleeue it, and beleeuing it, doe glorifie God and are ſaued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And be glorified.</hi> He deſireth that the worde of God may haue his force and efficacie to reforme men into the Image of God. Therfore holines of life and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity in chriſtians, is the beauty of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: euen as they doe bring infamie and ſlaunder to the Goſpell, profeſſing it with their mouth, and liuing neuertheleſſe fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thylie and wickedlie.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.15.</note> To this ende par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the exhortations of our ſauiour
<pb facs="tcp:2186:69"/> Chriſt, of Peter, and of others,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.12.</note> in the new Teſtament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euen as it is with you.</hi> That is to ſay, after the ſame manner, forme, and happie ſucceſſe. For this ought to be a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to the Godly, that they may ſee all other men like to them ſelues in godlineſſe. Therefore they which are already entered into the kingdome of God, are commaunded to pray daily that the ſame kingdome may come, ſo farre off they ought to be from enuie, when they do heare that others are come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>And that we may be deliuered from vnreaſonable and euill men: for all men haue not faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the latter cauſe, why the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle requireth the prayers of the faithfull. The truth indeed was preached: but in the meane time there ſprange vp diuers ſciſmes, among them alſo which would ſeeme to be the embracers of true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And the publike enimies of religion did both baniſh the truth, and did alſo moſt cruelly perſecute them which were maintainers of the truth: neither did
<pb facs="tcp:2186:70"/> there want certaine hypocrites and falſe brethren, which were worſe &amp; far more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they, vnto true godlineſſe. For it is truly ſaid, that a counterfeit frend is much more hurtfull then an open enimie. Wherefore Paul deſireth to be deliuered from ſuch. For by vnreaſonable and euill me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he meaneth thoſe, which vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of chriſtians, lurked in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church, or elſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, which through a mad zeale of the law, furiouſly perſecuted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel. For he knew how great harme was like to come by them both. And this ſaying of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle may be extended to all manner of perils. For then Paul was going to <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and did write, being in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of his iorney. But it was already told him from aboue that bondes and perſecutions wayted for him there.<note place="margin">Act. 20.23.</note> From the which he doth deſire to be ſo deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that he may ouercome whether it be by death, or by life. But now at this day, the miniſters of the word, haue the Pope and Papiſtes for their principall aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, which are in dede vnreaſonable and euill men, which doe hinder the courſe of the doctrine of the Goſpell with their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations,
<pb facs="tcp:2186:70"/> and doe deſtroy ſo much as li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in them, the fruit &amp; glorie of the word of God preached. There are beſide theſe, many wicked teachers, which thruſt in many peruerſe and fanaticall thinges, in their doings, as the <hi>Anabaptiſtes, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertine, Epicures, Atheiſtes,</hi> and ſuch like. Wherefore the Church ought to pray for the miniſters of the worde, that they may be deliuered from vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and euill men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For all men haue not faith.</hi> The reaſon whereby he proueth that vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and euill men are enemies and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors of the worde of God, is taken from faith, which is the ſingular gift of God. For God calleth many, which doe not come in faith: many alſo doe faine to come, but they are fartheſt off in heart. But Paul doth not ſpeake of euery one: for the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> did ſee, that very many did forſake the faith: yea they ſawe how ſmall the nomber of the beleeuers was. Wherefore this had beene ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous to be ſpoken: but Paul denieth, that all they which profeſſe the faith, are faithfull in deede. For many are called,<note place="margin">Mat. 20.16.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:2186:71"/> but fewe are choſen. If thou doeſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend all the Iewes, they ſeemed to be neere vnto Chriſt, who ought to haue knowne him by the lawe and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. But Paul in very deed, doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially note thoſe, with whome he was afterward to haue to doe. And it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry like that theſe were they, who hauing a ſhew and name of godlineſſe,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note> were not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding far from the ſame. Hereof came the conflict. Therefore if it ſhall fall out that thou haue to doe with vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and euill men, of the which there are alwayes a great multitude, thou ſhalt conſider that faith is no common thing, and that the ſame is not giuen but to Gods elect, &amp; to ſuch as are predeſtinate vnto eternall life. Whereupon it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the faith of Gods elect.<note place="margin">Tit. 1.1.</note> Therefore when we doe heare that the Church is troubled with wicked factions, let this be our buckler againſt ſuch ſtumbling bluckes of offence. For we ſhalbe often times iniurious, not onely to godly tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, if we doe doubt of their faith, ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as domeſticall enemies doe trouble them: but alſo our faith ſhall afterward
<pb facs="tcp:2186:71"/> wauer, except we ſhall remember that many are vnfaithfull among them which boaſt of the name of Chriſtians. Many therefore haue a counterfeit faith, forſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as al do not beleeue the Goſpel. 3 <hi>But the Lorde is faithful, which will ſtabliſh you, and keepe you from euill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He hath ſpoken of the perils with the which ſome men might be turned away from the faith. For there are many vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and euill men which doe vexe the Church of God many wayes, and doe deſtroy and corrupt the ſame, either with wicked doctrine, either with profane or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, or elſe with the crueltie of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions. Therefore the Apoſtle hath added another ſpeciall conſolation, by which they which haue beleeued the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell and are in the foreſaid troubles, may hope well for the preſence of Gods helpe, For it cannot be, that God will faile ſuch, but will ſtrengthen them, and deliuer them from euill. Moreouer becauſe it may be that their mindes being terrified with ſiniſter rumors, they came into ſome doubt of Pauls miniſterie: after
<pb facs="tcp:2186:72"/> that he hath admoniſhed them that faith is not alwayes to be found in men, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them backe vnto God, and ſaith that he is faithfull, which will confirme and ſtrengthen them againſt all the practiſes of men, with the which they ſhall goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to aſſayle them. As if he ſhould ſay, they indeed are falſe and vntruſtie, but yet God is able inough to hold you vp that you doe not fal. The ſumme is this, he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth that the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> through the helpe of God, ſhall abide in the faith: and withall he declareth that conſtancie in the faith, is the gift of God. He calleth the Lorde faithfull, which is conſtant in the defending of the ſaluation of his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, which helpeth them in due time, and neuer forſaketh them in perils. After the ſame manner we doe ſee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Church is often times afflicted, &amp; is in great perils of afflictions and temptations, and yet notwithſtanding, the ſame is preſerued &amp; deliuered out of all euils. For God is faithfull,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.13.</note> which will not ſuffer you to be tempted aboue that which you are able to beare. For as he alone is able, ſo he will helpe them that are tempted, and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,
<pb facs="tcp:2186:72"/> &amp; keepe them, that they be not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come in the afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore our faith and pacience is to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in aduerſities, and al the godly muſt looke for helpe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, who wil not faile to helpe them in due &amp; conuenient time. 4 <hi>And we are perſuaded of you through the Lorde, that ye both doe and will doe the thinges, which we commaund you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words are in effect thus much, we ſpeake theſe things not that we doubt of your conſtancie: nay we are aſſured of you, through the helpe of the Lord Ieſus, that ye will doe thoſe thinges hereafter which we commaund you to doe. This forme of ſpeaking if we aptly vſe, we ſhal preuaile more with them with whom we haue to doe, then if we vrge them with ſharpe reprehenſions, and harde threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings: for it is not the office of a teacher of the Goſpell to vſe alway ſharpe threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and reprehenſions, neither yet at all times gentle and milde exhortations, but herein to be diſcrete according to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſion, that he may retaine them in Godlineſſe, whom he hath vnder his
<pb facs="tcp:2186:73"/> charge to reforme. And by this preface Paul maketh a way for him ſelfe to the precept or commaundement which he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in the ſixt verſe following. For the confidence, and perſwaſion which he ſaith he hath of them, made them much more prompt and ready to obey, then if he had required their obedience, as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſting or doubting of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Through the Lorde.</hi> Paul doth not leane ſo much in perſwaſion on the <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians,</hi> as he doth in truſt &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence on the moſt faithfull God. And therefore he ſayeith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this hope which he hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of them is founded in the Lord: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it belongeth vnto him to bowe the harts of men vnto ſubmiſſion, &amp; to retaine them in the ſame. Or elſe herby he would declare (which is more likely) that he did not intend to commaund any thing, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which he had receiued warrant for from the Lorde. Therfore he determined thus w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him ſelfe, that both his commaunding, and their obeying, ſhould be in the Lorde. Wherefore whoſoeuer doe not retaine this modeſtie, doe in vaine pretend the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Paul, to bind &amp; tie the Church with their lawes. Peraduenture alſo it
<pb facs="tcp:2186:73"/> may be that he had a regard to maintaine the reuerence of his Apoſtleſhippe among the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> though the wicked went about to deface the ſame.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>And the Lorde guide your hearts to the loue of God, and the waiting for of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe wordes the Apoſtle wiſheth vnto the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> helpe &amp; ſtrength from the Lorde, that they may doe thoſe things which he commaundeth them out of the word of the Lorde. The ende of this prayer is, that we may al vnderſtand that euery good gift is giuen to vs from aboue, leaſt any man ſhould aſcribe to much to his owne ſtrength. The Lorde (ſaith he) ſo direct and gouerne you in true loue toward God, that ye may doe his commaundements: and alſo in faith toward Chriſt, that ye may ſhewe your ſelues patient in al troubles of afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Charitie wil make you to endeuour your ſelues continually to behaue your ſelues well towards all men: euen as God is good &amp; louing to all. The wayting for the comming of Chriſt, will make you ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſuffer all afflictions. Therefore we doe vnderſtand by the name of the loue of
<pb facs="tcp:2186:74"/> God in this place, that loue of ours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes God, by which we performe his commaundementes with prompt obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, honouring him which loued vs firſt, and gaue his onely begotten ſonne,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 4.10.</note> to be the obtayner of mercie for our ſinnes. For that true and effectuall loue is the ſtrength of ſuch as beleeue the Goſpell of Chriſt, which all they declare to be in them which are indued with a true faith in Chriſt. He prayeth alſo that the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full may without doubting, waite for the comming of Chriſt the defender of the afflicted, and that at the laſt they might be deliuered from their affliction. For the Apoſtle commonly vſeth to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ſuch as are afflicted, and himſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with the expectation of the comming of the iudge Chriſt. For thus he writeth, <hi>If we ſuffer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.11. 2. Tim. 4.</note> 
               <hi>we ſhal alſo raigne with him.</hi> And againe, <hi>From henceforth is laid vp for me the croune of righteouſneſſe, which the Lorde the righteous iudge ſhall giue me, at that day: and not to me onely, but vnto all them alſo which loue his comming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, ſeeing he doth here briefly
<pb facs="tcp:2186:74"/> expreſſe thoſe things which he knewe to be moſt neceſſarie for Chriſtians, if we deſire to grow to perfection, let vs ſeeke to profite in theſe two things. And in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deede the loue of God cannot raigne in vs, but that the loue of our brother muſt be in vs alſo. Alſo the looking for Chriſt inſtructeth Chriſtians to contemne the worlde, to mortifie the fleſh, and to beare the croſſe. Howbeit that may be expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be the wayting for Chriſt, which the doctrine of Chriſt doth beget in vs, that is to ſay, by which we ſuffer ſundry perſecutions of corporall afflictions for the name and glorie of Chriſt. But it is better to vnderſtand it of the hope of the laſt redemption.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>We commaund you brethren in the name of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, that ye withdrawe your ſelues from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery brother that walketh inordinat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not after the inſtruction which he receiued of vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is another exhortation concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſhunning of the company of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate brethren. The cauſe of this commaundement was, for that immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly
<pb facs="tcp:2186:75"/> after the Apoſtles times, certaine curious perſons, began to thruſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into the Church of God: who, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnder the pretence of religion, or elſe by ſiniſter meanes, that is to ſay, by idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſought to liue a pleaſant life. Theſe he calleth inordinate men, not that they were of a diſſolute life, or infamed with notorious crimes, but becauſe they were idle and ſlothfull perſons, which exerciſed themſelues in no honeſt trade of life. For this is a confuſed diſorder in deed, to haue no regard wherefore we are made, and not to frame our life to this ende. For this is a well ordered life, when we liue, according to the rule of Gods worde. Without this order, there is nothing in the life of man but confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And this is worthy to be noted, leaſt any man ſhould conceiue a liking of him ſelfe, liuing out of his lawfull vocation. For God hath put ſuch a difference in the life of men, that one man cannot liue without another. Therefore he which liueth to himſelfe onely, is no way profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to mankind, but a burthen to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Wherfore Paul pronounceth that
<pb facs="tcp:2186:75"/> ſuch are to be driuen out of the company of the faithfull, leaſt they bring ſhame and infamie to the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the name of our Lorde Ieſu Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle added this, that the <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians</hi> might vnderſtand, that this commaundement ought to be reuerently receiued, as comming, not from a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man, but from Chriſt himſelfe. As if he ſhould ſaye, thoſe thinges which we commaund you, we doe not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund as in our owne name, but by the commaundement of Chriſt our Lorde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That ye withdraw your ſelues from euery brother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This withdrawing whereof he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, doth not appertaine to publique ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, but to priuate cuſtome, or company keeping. For he doth ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plely forbid, that the faithfull haue no manner of familiaritie with ſuch idle droanes, as haue no honeſt trade of life wherein they may liue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That walketh inordinately.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Leaſt any man ſhould take this word <hi>inordinatly,</hi> in another meaning, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
<pb facs="tcp:2186:76"/> Apoſtle Paul himſelfe vnderſtood, he wil expound him ſelfe in the eleuenth verſe following. And he doth here make mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by name of brethren, who being ſuch, and profeſſing themſelues to be Chriſtians, of all others are leaſt to be tollerated, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are as it were the blots and ſpots of religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And not after the inſtitution which he receiued of vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the inſtitution, he meaneth that, which he will adde anone in the tenth verſe, that meate be not giuen to him which will not labour.</p>
            <p n="7">7 <hi>For ye your ſelues knowe how ye ought to followe vs: for we behaued not our ſelues inordinately among you:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 <hi>Neyther tooke we bread of any man for nought, but we wrought with labour and trauell night and day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we would not be chargeable to any of you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before the Apoſtle commeth to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, he ſheweth what manner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample he hath giuen them in him ſelfe. For that doctrine is of great credit and
<pb facs="tcp:2186:76"/> authoritie, when we laye no more bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then vpon others, then we take vpon our ſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For we behaued not our ſelues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinately among you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As if he ſhould ſay, there is iuſt cauſe why ye ſhould follow me, for I haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued an honeſt, Godly, and Chriſtian life among you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neither tooke we bread of any man for nought.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He proueth that he did not behaue him ſelfe inordinately among the <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> and withall he doth by the way re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend thoſe, which vnder the pretence of the Goſpell liue idlely, and are a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then to others. He ſheweth that he wrought day and night with his handes, that he might not be chargeable to any man. Of the which matter he had ſaid ſomewhat in the former Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 2.9.</note> And whereas he denieth that he hath eaten any mans bread frely or of gift, in very deed he ſhould not haue done ſo, although he had not laboured with h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s handes. For it is not of free gift, which is due by right: and the price of
<pb facs="tcp:2186:77"/> the labour which the Miniſters of the Goſpell beſtow on the Church is much greater, then the liuing which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, from the ſame. But Paul had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect here, vnto diſordered &amp; careles men. For al men are not ſo equal &amp; indifferent, that they will acknowledge the reward which is due vnto the miniſters of the word. But rather ſuch is the malice of ſome, that although they doe giue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of their owne, yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they doe grudge them neceſſarie li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, as if they were idle men. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome by the example of Paul, doe conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly affirme, that nothing is to be pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at al to godly Biſhops, and miniſters: but theſe men, if they would conſider the circumſtances of the place, time, and perſons, and for what cauſes, euery thing was done, they ſhould wel ſee and know, that Paul did this for no other cauſe, but onely for charitie, that others might not be offended. It is certaine that he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued nothing of the <hi>Corinthyans:</hi> but for the falſe Apoſtles ſake, he neglected his owne power and libertie, leaſt they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Paul for their example, might ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="tcp:2186:77"/> haue ſome colour to excuſe their gaine. For it is moſt certaine that Paul tooke contribution of the brethren of <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia.</hi> And anone he will declare,<note place="margin">Phil. 4.25.</note> that he departed from his proper right, when he tooke no ſtipend. Whereby he giueth to vnderſtand that it is leſſe tollerable, that they which doe nothing, ſhould liue of contribution. He writeth alſo,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.13.</note> that they muſt liue of the Goſpell, which preach the Goſpell: and alſo that they muſt be had in high reputation through loue, for their works ſake.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.13 1. Tim. 5.17.</note> And in another place he ſaith, that they which gouerne well, are worthy of double honour. The like almoſt is to be red in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Galathyans.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.6. Heb. 13.7</note> And in the Epiſtle to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Hebrewes</hi> it is written: <hi>Remember thoſe which haue the ouerſight of you, which haue declared vnto you the worde of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are very many teſtimonies, to proue that neceſſarie maintenance,<note place="margin">Luke. 10.7.</note> a ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, double honour, contribution, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bends, and benifices, belong vnto the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpell.<note place="margin">Mat. 10.8.</note> And whereas ſome aleadge this ſentence: <hi>Freely ye haue
<pb facs="tcp:2186:78"/> receiued, giue freely:</hi> the ſame is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing repugnant to the former ſentence, which is, <hi>That the labourer is worthy of his hier.</hi> For in this place two things are commaunded, firſt that the diſciples ſhould comfort the weake, and put away diſeaſes, without taking any mony for the ſame, becauſe they did it by the power of Chriſt, who would not haue the giftes of the holy Ghoſt to be ſold, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by the example of <hi>Simon Magus.</hi> The ſecond is, that the due hier and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, be giuen to the labourer. To Chriſt alſo and to the Apoſtles, the neceſſarie maintenance of life, was giuen by others: as appeareth in the Goſpell of Luke.<note place="margin">Luke. 8.2.3.</note> But let vs returne againe to the wordes of Paul: who addeth ſaying:</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9 Not, but that we had authoritie, but that we might make our ſelues an enſample vnto you to follow vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As Paul intended to giue an example by his labour, leaſt ſlothfull men ſhould, like idle droanes, eate vp the hony which belonged to the painfull bees: euen ſo he would not haue his example hurtfull to the miniſters of the word, that the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb facs="tcp:2186:78"/> thereby ſhould defraud them of their lawfull maintenance. Wherein we may behold the ſingular moderation, diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and humanitie of the Apoſtle, and how farre he was from the ambition of thoſe men, which abuſe their vertues, and giftes to this ende, that they may demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the right of their brethren. It was to be feared leaſt the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the Goſpel preached vnto them free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the mouth of Paul, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, would (according to the malicious nature of man) make the ſame a law for other miniſters. Paul to mete with this preiudice, and inconuenience, teacheth that he hath power and authoritie to doe more then he did: this he doth that he might not reſtraine others of their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And by this reaſon he would make the idle and ſlowbellies aſhamed the more: as we haue before touched. For it is an argument from the greater to the leſſe. Therefore that right ought to be ſafely keept and defended, as graunted from God, and confirmed by the law of nature, becauſe the labourer is worthy of his reward. Except, the time, occaſion,<note place="margin">Luke. 10.7.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:2186:79"/> and other circumſtances perſwade to the contrarie. For then the miniſter of the Goſpell muſt be content to leaue ſome parte of his right, leaſt he giue offence to the Goſpel of Chriſt. For what wil come to paſſe, if they that be teachers, through coueteouſneſſe, wil depart from nothing? Therefore it is euident enough, how far Paul would haue his example to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, in that he would not be ſuſtayned with the coſt of the Church. For in all thinges, we ought to ſeeke eſpecially the glorie of the Goſpel: and it belongeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to charitie, that we endeuour our ſelues, not to be grieuous and offenſiue to any. It is not lawful to be too chargeable and coſtly to the Churches, neyther is it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the Churches to refuſe to giue and contribute liberally to their mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, when they are able. Concerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which matter, read more in the 9. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the 1. Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthyans.</hi> 10 <hi>For euen when we were with you, this we warned you of, that if there were any which would not worke, that he ſhould not eate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon why the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2186:79"/> ought to imitate Paul, is taken from the inſtitution going before, concerning the not ſuffering of thoſe, which vnder the pretence of the Goſpell, follow idleneſſe, and oppreſſe others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That if there were any which would not worke he ſhould not eate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the very law and ordinance wherof he ſpake in the ſixt verſe. For ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is written,<note place="margin">Pſal. 128.</note> 
               <hi>Thou art bleſſed ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the labour of thy hands:</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>The bleſſing of the Lorde is vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the handes of him that worketh:</hi> It is certaine that ſlothfulneſſe and idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is likewiſe curſed of the Lord. Alſo we knowe that man was created to doe ſome thing: as not onely the Scripture teſtifieth, but as nature alſo hath taught the Gentiles. Whereupon they haue made many Prouerbs. He that feareth the mil, ſhal haue no meale. Alſo, there is no hony without the bee. For he which cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide bees, becauſe of their prickes, is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to poſſeſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hony. Againe, thou ſuffereſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which hurteth, that thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt poſſeſſe the profite. It is therfore meet &amp; right that they which exempt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon law which appertayneth
<pb facs="tcp:2186:80"/> to all men, be alſo depriued of liuing, and of the reward of labour. Theſe things if Kinges and Chriſtian Princes had well conſidered foure hundred yeares agoe, they had had more plentie of riches, and fewer monkes. For how doe the whole rowt and rable of the pouleſhorne po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe clergie, adorne the Goſpell? and what profite do they bring to the church? the great multitude whereof, what doth it containe, but ſluggiſh, and idle perſons, lazie lubbers, ſlowbellies, couetous and ambitious Prieſtes, fornicators, and all manner of lewd and wicked perſons, men vnlearned, and vtterly ignorant of the holy Scriptures, and beſide this, the moſt cruell enimies to the doctrine of the faith in Chriſt? Who notwithſtanding doe ſwimme in the welth and riches of the Church (in other countries) at their pleaſure, and liue like fatte hogges in the ſtye. In whom moſt aptly are fulfilled theſe wordes of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>They count it pleaſure to liue deliciouſly for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Spots they are and blots, deliting themſelues in their deceiuings, in fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting with you, hauing eyes full of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulterie,
<pb facs="tcp:2186:80"/> and that cannot ceaſe to ſinne, beguiling vnſtable ſoules. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer by theſe wordes of Paul, as with thunderclappes from heauen, the rites, ordinances, and rules of begging friers, and monkes being touched, are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne, who being a counterfeit ſort of pore, do notwithſtanding fill their bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies with other mens trenchers, whom a man moſt truly may call idle droanes. For this kind of beggery of all other, is moſt wicked and vngodly, and no better then a kind of rapine and theft.</p>
            <p>Furthermore we muſt note that there are diuers kinds of labouring. For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he be that doth any manner of way ſeeke to benefite the ſociety of men by his induſtrie, whether it be in gouerning a familie, or in dealing in publique or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate affayres, eyther in counſayling, or in teaching, or by any other manner, of way, the ſame is not to be reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong idle perſons. For the Apoſtle here ſpeaketh againſt idle droanes, which liue by the ſweate of other mens browes, they themſelues doing nothing to benefite the common wealth.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <pb facs="tcp:2186:81"/>11 <hi>For we heard that there are ſome, which walke among you inordinatly, and woorke not at all, but are buſie bodies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now he doth ſpeake more plainely &amp; ſtrictly of that, which hetherto he hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken at large. The cauſe (ſayth he) why I do ſo greatly vrge theſe things, is, for that I doe heare, that ſome do liue inordinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly among you, that is, doing no woorke at all, but curiouſly buſying them ſelues. It is very like that this kinde of ſlothful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, was a certaine ſede of idle monkery, for eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the very begining of the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue church, there were ſome which vnder the colour of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, did rob other mens tables, or els did ſubtilly drawe vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, the ſubſtance and riches of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And in <hi>Auguſtines</hi> time they had ſo greatly preuayled, that hee was conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to write a ſpeciall booke againſt idle Moonkes: wherein he doth iuſtely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of their pride, who contemning the admonition of the Apoſtell, doe not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excuſe them ſelues of infirmitie, but alſo will therefore ſeeme to be more holy than other men, becauſe they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb facs="tcp:2186:81"/> not. But this miſchefe hath ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed and ouerflowed, that ſlowe bellies haue almoſt poſſeſſed the tenth parte of the earth, whoſe onely Religion is this, to haue their bellies well filled, and to giue them ſelues from labour, to eaſe and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. And this vile kinde of life they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend with this title, or that name of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. But what doth Paule by the mouth of the ſpirit one the contrary parte pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce? verely he pronounceth them al to be irregular &amp; diſordered, with what title ſoeuer they be couered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And woorke not at all, but are buſie bodies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is to ſaye, liuing idlely vnder the cloake of the Goſpell, and hating others. By theſe woordes he doth expound what it is to liue inordinately.</p>
            <p>And he noteth a ſpeciall vice, with the which idle men are infected, namely that they are troubleſome to themſelues, and to others, by being importunate medlers, and buſie bodies. For we doe ſee by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon experience, that thoſe men which haue nothing to doe, are much more wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie doing nothing, then if they were buſie,
<pb facs="tcp:2186:82"/> and occupied about a very ſerious worke. They runne hyther and thither: whether ſoeuer they come, they make a ſhew of wearineſſe: they gather vp all the tales that they heare, and buſily diſperſe them abroad againe. A man would thinke that they carried vpon their ſhoulders the waight of a kingdome. Can we haue a more euident example of this matter in any other ſort, then in the monkes? For what ſorte of men are more vnquiet? Where doth there raigne greater curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? Alſo in this place, thoſe which are Biſhops &amp; Paſtors only in name, are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which haue no care of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords flock, but are onely curious in thoſe thinges, which ſerue to maintaine voluptuouſnes, coueteouſneſſe, oppreſſion, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>Therefore them that are ſuch we commaund and exhorte, by our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that they woorke with quietneſſe, and eate their owne bread</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the inormities of the Church men ought not to winke, neither are idle and curious men, vnder the pretence of the Goſpell, to be tollerated in the Church. Therfore Paul vſeth now a more ſeuere
<pb facs="tcp:2186:82"/> and ſharpe reprehenſion, leaſt ſuch men flatter themſelues in that kind of life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By our Lorde Ieſu Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the end all men may know that he doth not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his owne name, but by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement and authoritie of the Lorde Chriſt, he hath added this. Notwithſtanding the worde of exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, doth ſignifie that he doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue himſelfe imperiouſly, or that he would rule, but that he would doe all things according to his office.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That they worke with quietneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He correcteth both thoſe vices, of the which he had made mention afore, namely troubleſome vnquiet medling, and idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe from profitable labour. Firſt of all therefore he commaundeth that they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace quietnes: that is to ſay, that they do quietly keepe themſelues within the boundes of their vocation. For they are moſt quiet of all others which occupie themſelues in honeſt labours: but they doe both trouble themſelues and others, which haue no worke to doe. Secondly he exhorteth them to labour: that is to ſay, that they buſie &amp; occupy themſelues
<pb facs="tcp:2186:83"/> diligently in their vocation: and that they be doing in iuſt and honeſt exerciſes, without the which, the life of man is erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious. Therefore to woorke with quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, is to labor in their vocation without curiouſity: and ſo to follow their laboures, that they doe not raſhlye meddle in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens functions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And eate their owne breade.</hi> Thereby he commaundeth that they eat their owne bread: whereby hee giueth to vnderſtand that they muſt bee contented with their owne, that they bee not gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and troubleſome to others. <hi>Drink</hi> (ſayth Solomon) <hi>the Water of thine owne ceſtern,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prouerb. 5.</note> 
               <hi>and of the riuers out of the middeſt of thine owne well: Let thy fountaynes flowe foorth, and the riuers of waters in the ſtreetes.</hi> This is the firſt rule of equity, that no man vſurp that which is another mans, but vſe that onely which is his owne: and which lawfully he may cal his own. The ſecond is, that no man like a greedy gulfe do ſwalow vp al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is his, by himſelf alone, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he be beneficiall to his neighbors, &amp; do help their need w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Let al
<pb facs="tcp:2186:83"/> idle bellies, conſider theſe thinges, and al biſhops falſely ſo called, abbots, priors, Moonkes, and ſuch like. Let them heare I ſay the Apoſtle commaunding and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting by our Lorde Ieſus, that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with quietneſſe they eate their owne bread, and ceaſe to be grieuous vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and let them be aſhamed that they haue filthily and wickedly waſted and ſpoyled the goods of the Church. Let them forſake their office, and commit the charge of eccleſiaſticall miniſtration to meete and worthy men, leaſt they bring deſtruction to others: and much leſſe let them vexe the Churches through their wicked cenſures, vnprofitable lawes, and hurtfull conſtitutions. Or elſe if they will ſtill retaine their offices, let them do that which becommeth their Apoſtolicall charge, let them ſerue the honor of Chriſt, and let them not want any thing concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the doctrine of the Goſpell: let them haue care of the pore, and preſerue ſcholes for the maintenance of godly learning. For thoſe Biſhoppes and Paſtors, which are negligent in theſe thinges, doing the contrarie, are vnprofitable and hurtfull,
<pb facs="tcp:2186:84"/> and not to be tollerated in the Church of God. Finally this place maketh againſt the Anabaptiſts, who deny that it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for a Chriſtian man to haue any thing of his owne. But Paul commaundeth euery man to worke quietly that he may eate his owne bread.</p>
            <p n="13">13 <hi>And ye brethren, be not weary of well doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third exhortation is, concerning well doing and liberalitie, the which is very neceſſarie in the conſeruation of a well ordered Church. But the purpoſe of Paul in this place was ſimplely to meete with a ſtumbling blocke, which might come of the negligence of a few. For it is commonly ſene that men which of themſelues are very liberall, when they ſee that they leeſe their benifites, in beſtowing them amiſſe, doe withdrawe their hand. Paul therefore exhorteth vs, how vnworthy ſoeuer many be, or how greatly ſoeuer ſome doe abuſe our libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, that we doe not therefore ceaſe, but doe helpe ſtill thoſe which haue neede of our helpe.<note place="margin">Gal. 6.6.</note> Thus in another place he ſaith, <hi>Let vs not therefore be weary of well
<pb facs="tcp:2186:84"/> doing: for in due ſeaſon we ſhal reape, if we faint not.</hi> This ſentence is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be noted, howſoeuer the vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, frowardneſſe, pride, peuiſhneſſe, and other indignities may wearie vs, yet we ought to goe forward ſtill in well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and neuer be diſcouraged from the ſame. There are many places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which do commend liberalitie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the poore, eſpecially theſe. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 58.7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.40. <hi>Luke.</hi> 6.38. and 11.41. and 16.9. <hi>Prou.</hi> 11.25. and 19.17. and 21.13. and 22.16. and 28.27. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17.</p>
            <p n="14">14 <hi>If any man obey not our ſayings, note him by a letter, and haue no company with him, that he may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the laſt exhortation concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the puniſhment of the diſobedient. He hath already teſtified in the ſixt verſe, that he doth commaund nothing, but in the name of the Lord. Wherfore he which will not obey, ſhal not be diſobedient vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man, but rebellious againſt God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Therefore he teacheth that ſuch are ſharpely to be puniſhed: and firſt of al
<pb facs="tcp:2186:85"/> he requireth that he may vnderſtande of their names by a certayne epiſtle, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing admoniſhed by Paul, and more ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently terrified, they might returne into the right way. Furthermore hee commaundeth that they bee excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, that being made aſhamed they may repent.</p>
            <p>Whereby we gather that their fame is not to bee ſpared which can not bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe reformed, but by the diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of their wickedneſſes: but we muſt take heede that wee ſhewe the diſeaſes to the Phiſition, which hath a care to heal them. But the apoſtle ſpeaketh eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialy of thoſe, which liued lewdly in idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, of whom we haue already ſpoken.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And haue no company with him.</hi> There is no doubt but that hee ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of excommunication. For as the confuſed diſorder which he noted before, deſerued a ſeuerall puniſhment, euen ſo contumacy is a vice intollerable. Before he had ſayd,<note place="margin">Verſe. 6.</note> 
               <hi>withdraw your ſelues from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which liue diſorderedly:</hi> And now he ſaith, keepe no company with ſuch, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do reiect my admonition. Hee
<pb facs="tcp:2186:85"/> doth therefore expreſſe more in this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſpeach, then hee did in the former. For it is one thing to withdrawe himſelf from the company of a man, and another thing vtterly to forſake the company of one. The ſame is this, that he excludeth them from the common company of the faithfull, becauſe they being admoniſhed, did not obey. Whereby we are taught that the diſcipline of excommunication is to be vſed againſt all incorrigible, and obſtinat perſons, which will not bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, vntill they being ſubdued and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, do learne to obey.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That he may be aſhamed.</hi> Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Diſcipline is not appointed to deſtroy but to ſaue. Wherefore the ſinner is not vtterly to bee forſaken and ſhaken off, but hee is ſo to bee ſhunned, that being ſecluded for a time from the companye of the faythfull, hee maye at the laſt repent. There are alſo other endes of excommunication, as that the contagion maye not further increaſe, and that the pryuate wickedneſſe of one man doe not redounde to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monne ſhame of the Churche, and
<pb facs="tcp:2186:86"/> alſo that the example of ſeueritie may cauſe others to feare: but Paul hath here touched one thing only, namely that they which haue ſinned, may through ſhame be drawne to repentance. For they which haue pleaſure in their wickedneſſe, are hardened more and more therein: thus ſinne is foſtered through indulgence, and diſſimulation. This therefore is the beſt Remedie, to make the ſinner aſhamed, that he may begin to miſlike of himſelfe. This of it ſelfe without further proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, were to ſmall purpoſe, for a man to be aſhamed: but Paul had regarde to a further proceding, as that the ſinner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made aſhamed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the acknowledging of his filthines, might therby perfectly be reformed. For ſhame is a profitable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiue to the hatred of ſin, euen as is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſorrow, whereof mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is made in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth Chapter of the ſecond Epiſtle to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Corinthians,</hi> verſe 10. Wherefore they are to be reſtrayned and checked with this bit, which are vnrulie leſt boldneſſe doe increace by impunitie.</p>
            <p n="15">15 <hi>Yet count him not as an eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, but admoniſh him as a brother.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2186:86"/>
            <p>Becauſe excommunication is inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a good and profitable ende, the ſame muſt be executed, according to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and not of hatred and euill will. Therefore the diſobedient, are to be ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, not as enimies, but they are to be warned as brethren: otherwiſe being forſaken they might be diſcouraged, or elſe might more obſtinately withſtand Chriſtian ſocietie. Therefore they being warned as brethren, excommunication is a meane to bring them to repentaunce. For it cannot be but that ſeueritie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding a meaſure, doth exulcerate &amp; fret.</p>
            <p>Therfore if we will doe good, gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and lenitie muſt neceſſarilie be vſed, that they which are reprehended. may neuertheleſſe know that they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued. And this end of eccleſiaſticall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, is eſpecially to be noted. For the Apoſtle would not haue vs to abhor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that we might preferre our ſelues before them in holineſſe: or pleaſing our ſelues might ſhew tyranny toward the miſerable: but that the ſinner being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended of vs, may deſcend into him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and may acknowledge the filthines<pb facs="tcp:2186:87"/> of his wickedneſſe, and ſo beeing made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed may repent. For this is not the ende of excommunication to depriue and ſequeſter for euer, men from the flocke of Chriſte, but rather to call them home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne to the ſame, which were wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring out of the way. But if the malice of him that hath ſinned be ſuch that hee will not repent, then let deliberation be had, by what meanes the obſtinate ſinner may beſt bee holpen, that eyther he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf do not wholy periſh, or els that hee doe not corrupte others with his ſcab.</p>
            <p n="16">16 <hi>Nowe the Lorde of peace giue you peace alwayes, by all meanes. The Lorde bee with you all.</hi> This is his farewell, by which he firſt wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto them peace: aſwell externall as internall from God the authour of peace: then he wiſheth vnto them the helpe of God againſt the aſſaultes of Inuaſions of Chriſtianiſme. Laſt of all hee deſireth that they may haue ſaluation and good ſucceſſe of all thinges through Chriſte our Lorde. Hee calleth GOD the
<pb facs="tcp:2186:87"/> Lorde of peace, becauſe hee is the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour and giuer of concorde, of lenity, and of charity, euen as Sathan is the Prince and authour of diſcorde, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, brawles, of enuy, and of diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lorde bee with you all.</hi> By this petition hee wiſheth to the Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians the protection, and defence of the Lorde. As if he ſhoulde ſaye, The Lorde bee your guide and gouernour, who protect and defende you, and ſo proſper all your affayres, diſpoſe, order, and direct al your doings, that they may bee to the honour of his name, and profitable to you and to the whole Church,</p>
            <p n="17">17 <hi>The ſalutation of mee Paule, with my owne hande, which is the token in euerye Epiſtle: So I write,</hi> Heere agayne the Apoſtle prouideth for that perill, whereof hee hadde made mention in the ſeconde Verſe of the ſeconde Chapter goinge beefore, leaſte thoſe Epiſtles of the falſe Apoſtles, beeinge falſelye intituled, myghte bee craftielye conueyed into
<pb facs="tcp:2186:88"/> the Church. For this was an old practiſe of Sathan, to thruſt in falſe forged wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges, to diſcredite thoſe which were in deede true. And further, that by the falſe titles of the Apoſtles, he might ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad wicked errors, to corrupte hole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome doctrine. But it came to paſſe by the ſingular goodneſſe of God, that his ſubtill deceits being made fruſtrate, the holſome and pure doctrine of Chriſt, by the miniſterie of Paul, &amp; of others, is come vnto vs. Paul therefore very pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently prouided by that ſubſcription of of his owne hand, that the certaintie and truth of the Apoſtolicall letters, might be approued to all men. That no man afterward might complaine that he was deceiued, and bring the ſacred ſcriptures into doubt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus I write.</hi> That is to ſaye, this is the order and forme of wordes of the which I am wont to frame my ſalutatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the which I vſe as a certaine ſigne, and token of my Epiſtles. And for ſo much as he did conſtantly teach all nations, that mankinde was ſaued by grace, he taking his ſigne or ſubſcription from
<pb facs="tcp:2186:88"/> that principall point of religion, ſubſig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned the ſame note of faith at the ende of all the Epiſtles, writing as followeth in the 18. verſe.</p>
            <closer>The grace of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, be with you all, Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prophecies">
            <pb facs="tcp:2186:89"/>
            <head>Propheſies prouing the <hi>Pope to be Antichriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="prophecy">
               <head>Apocalips Chap. 13. verſe. 11.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>AND I behelde another beaſte, comming vp out of the earth, and he had two hornes like a lambe, and he ſpake as did the Dragon. And he doth al that the firſt beaſt could do in his preſence, and he cauſeth the earth and them that dwell therein to worſhippe the firſt beaſt, whoſe deadly wound was healed. And he doth great wonders, ſo that he maketh fire come downe from heauen on the earth in the ſight of men: And deceiueth them that dwell on the earth, by the meanes of thoſe ſignes, which he had power to doe in the ſight of the beaſt: ſaying to them that dwel on the earth, that they ſhold make an image to the beaſt which hath the wound of a ſworde, &amp; did liue. And he had power to giue a ſpirit vnto the image of the beaſt, that the image
<pb facs="tcp:2186:89"/> of the beaſt, ſhould both ſpeake, and ſhould cauſe that as many as would not worſhip the image of the beaſt, ſhould be killed. And he cauſeth all, both ſmall and great, riche and poore, free and bond, that he ſhould giue them a mark in their right hande, or in their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heades: And that no man mighte buy or ſell, ſaue he that had the marke, or the name of the beaſt, other the nomber of his name. Here is wiſedom. Let him that hath wit, count the nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the beaſt: for it is the nomber of a man, and his number is ſixe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſixtie, ſixe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the Popes friendes doe applie this Propheſie to <hi>Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> and the Turkes, yet it ſhall appeare by certaine reaſons fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing that it doth neceſſarily appertaine to the Biſhop of Rome and none other. The firſt reaſon is, for that this beaſt, is diſcribed to beare the hornes of a lambe. By the which lambe, no doubt is ment
<pb facs="tcp:2186:90"/> Chriſt. By the hornes of the lambe, is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified the outward ſhewe or reſemblance of Chriſt: which ſhew or reſemblance, can haue no relation to <hi>Mahumet,</hi> for that he taketh himſelfe to be aboue Chriſt, and Chriſt as an excellent Prophet of God ſitting at his feete. Wherefore ſeeing <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humet</hi> commeth neither as equall to Chriſt, nor as vicar vnder Chriſt, this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie cannot agree in him, but onely in the man, which openly and in plain words proteſteth, that all Chriſtes lambes and ſheepe, not ſingularly, but vniuerſally through the whole worlde, are committed to him as vicar of Chriſt, and ſucceſſor of Peter, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al men muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe the ſame of neceſſity, or elſe they are none of Chriſts ſheepe. Wherin it is eaſie to ſee, where the pretenced hornes of the lambe doe grow.</p>
               <p>The ſecond reaſon: <hi>And he ſpake like the Dragon. &amp;c.</hi> A lambes hornes and the mouth of a Dragon doe not agree to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather. And as they doe not agree to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather in nature, ſo neither can they be found in any one perſon, either Turke or other, ſo liuely as in the Biſhop of Rome. When thou heareſt him call him ſelfe the
<pb facs="tcp:2186:90"/> Apoſtolicall Byſhop, the vicar of Chriſt, the ſucceſſor of Peter, the ſeruaunt of Gods ſeruauntes &amp;c. Thou ſeeſt in him the two hornes of a lambe, and woulde thinke him to be a lambe indeed, and ſuch a one as woulde waſhe your feete for humilitie: but heare him ſpeake, and mark the behauiour, condition, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie, almoſte of all the Popes which haue beene theſe ſixe hundred yeeres: and what Dragon or ſerpent coulde be more viperouſe, then their owne doinges and woordes can ſpeake agaynſt themſelues.</p>
               <p>The thirde reaſon, <hi>And hee doth all the power of the firſt beaſte, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before his face, and cauſeth the earth and all the inhabitantes of the earth to honor the firſt beaſt, the ſtripe of whoſe deadly wound was cured. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this propheſie two thinges are to be noted: Firſt, what the firſt beaſt is, whoſe power the ſecond beaſte doth execute. Secondlie, what this ſeconde Beaſte is, which ſo doth exerciſe his power in his ſight. The firſt of theſe beaſts in this thirteenth chapter, hauing ſeuen heades, and ten hornes muſt needes
<pb facs="tcp:2186:91"/> ſignify the city of Rome, which may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily bee prooued by two demonſtrations. Firſt by the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>poſition of the ſeuenteene Chapter of the ſame Apocalyps, where is declared and deſcribed the ſayde beaſt to ſtande on ſeuen hilles, and to contayne ten kinges, hauing the whole power of the Dragon giuen: and alſo the ſame City to bee named the Whoore of Babylon, drunken with the bloude of Saynts. All which properties ioyned together, canne agree in no wiſe but onely to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Empyer of Rome: which Citye, at the time of writing theſe propheſies, had the gouernment of the whole worlde. The ſeconde demonſtration, maye bee brought out of the number of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths aſſigned to this Beaſte. For it is written in the aboue named Chapter, that this Beaſte had power to make, that is, to worke his malice againſt the members of the Church of Chriſte, forty two moneths. Which moneths counted by Sabbates of yeeres (that is, euery moneth for ſeuen yeeres) maketh vp the iuſt number of thoſe yeares, in which the primitiue Church, was vnder the tenne
<pb facs="tcp:2186:91"/> terrible perſecutions of Heathen Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of Rome.</p>
               <p>Which thing thus ſtanding, prooued and confeſſed, that the firſt Beaſte muſt needes ſignify the Empyre and Cyty of Rome, then muſt it neceſſarilye followe, that the ſeconde Beaſte with the Lambs Hornes, muſt ſignify the Byſhoppe and Pope of the ſame City of Rome. The reaſon whereof is euident and apparent by that which followeth in the propheſy, where it is declared, that the ſeconde beaſte hauing the two hornes of a Lamb, receiued and exerciſed all the power of the firſt Beaſte, before or in the ſighte of the ſayde Beaſte. Whiche cannot bee verified, neyther in the Turke nor in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other, but onely in the Pope of Rome: who receiueth, vſurpeth, and deriueth to himſelfe all the power of that City and Monarchie of Rome: inſomuch that he ſayth, that when <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> or <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douicus</hi> yeelded vnto him the rule and kingdome of the city of Rome, he gaue him but his owne, and that which of right and duety, belonged to him bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2186:92"/>
               <p>And this authority or power ouer all the Empyre of Rome, hee worketh not in Aſia, or in Conſtantinople, as the Turk doth, but in the ſight of the beaſt, which gaue him the power, that is, in the City of Rome it ſelfe, which is the firſt beaſt in the beginning of this 13. Chapter deſcribed.</p>
               <p>The fourth reaſon is, <hi>And hee cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the earth, and all the inhabitants therein, to worſhip and honoure the firſt beaſte, which had a deadly wound and was cured, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The interpretation of this part, as alſo of all the other partes of the ſame Chapter, ſtandeth vppon the definition of the firſt Beaſt. For beeing graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as it cannot be denied, that the firſt beaſte ſignifieth the City and Empyre of Rome: It muſt conſequentlye followe, that the Byſhop (whome wee call the Pope) of the ſame Citye of Rome, muſt bee vnderſtande by the ſeconde Beaſte: forſomuch as neyther Turke, nor anye other but onely the Byſhoppe of Rome, hath holden vp the eſtimation and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of that city, which began to be in ruine
<pb facs="tcp:2186:92"/> and decay by the Vandalians, Gotthes, Herulians, and Lombardes, about the yeare of our Lorde fowre hundred, fiftye ſixe. But afterwarde by the Byſhop of Rome the priſtine, ſtate and honoure of that City reuiued againe, and flouriſhed in as greate veneration as euer it did before. And that is it which the holye ghoſt ſeemeth heere to meane of the firſt Beaſt, ſaying: <hi>That hee had a wound of the ſwoorde, and was cured.</hi> For ſo it followeth.</p>
               <p>The fifth reaſon, <hi>And hee cauſed all the inhabitauntes of the earth to make the image of the beaſte, which had the ſtripe of the ſword and liued. And it was giuen to him, to giue life to the image of the Beaſt, and to make the image thereof to ſpeake, and to cauſe all them that worſhipped not the image of the Beaſte to bee killed: forcing all perſons both little and greate, riche and poore, bonde and free, to take the marke of the beaſte in their right hand, or in their foreheads: and that none mighte buye or ſell, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hey which had the mark, or the name
<pb facs="tcp:2186:93"/> of the beaſt, or the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of his name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By giuing life to the image of the beaſt, and making it to ſpeake, is to bee preſuppoſed, that the beaſte was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a neere poynt of death, and lay ſpeache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe afore, inſomuch that the Citye of Rome beganne to looſe and change his name, and was called a while, <hi>Odoacria,</hi> of <hi>Odoacer</hi> king of the Herulians, who by dint of ſword ſurpriſed the Romans: and yet notwithſtanding, by the meanes of this Romayn Prelate, the ſayde Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Rome, which was then readye to giue the Ghoſte, ſo recouered her maieſty and ſtrength agayne, that it is harde to ſaye, whether Rome did euer rufle and rage in her tyranny before, in the time of <hi>Nero, Domitian, Diocletian,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Emperours, more tragically, then it hath doone ſince vnder the Pope: or whether that Rome had all Kinges, Queenes, Princes, Dukes, Lordes, and all ſubiectes, more vnder obedience and ſubiection, when the Emperours raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or nowe in the raigne of the Pope. And therefore it is ſayde not without cauſe of the holy ghoſte, <hi>That it is giuen
<pb facs="tcp:2186:93"/> to him to giue life and ſpeeche to the image of the Beaſte, cauſing all them to bee ſlayne, which will not worſhip the image of the beaſte &amp;c.</hi> As for example hereof, who ſeethe not, what number and multitudes of Chriſtian men, Women, and Children, in all Countries, haue beene put to the fire and Sworde? Stories of all times will declare, what hauocke hath beene made of Chriſtian bloude about the preheminence and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iority of the ſea of Rome: what Churches and Countries, bothe Greekes and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, haue beene excommunicated: what Kinges haue beene depoſed, and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours ſtripped from their imperiall ſeate, and all becauſe they woulde not ſtoupe and bende to the image of the beaſt, that is to the maieſty and tytle of Rome, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunced nowe ſo highly by the Byſhop thereof, as it was neuer higher before in the reigne of <hi>Nero,</hi> or <hi>Diocletian.</hi> Wherefore taking the firſt beaſte to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify the Empyre of Rome (which cannot be denied) it is playne, that the ſeconde beaſte muſt neceſſarily be applied to the Pope, and not to the Turke, forſomuche
<pb facs="tcp:2186:94"/> as the Turke ſeeketh nothing leſſe then the aduauncement of that empyre, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtirreth againſt it to plucke it downe.</p>
               <p>The laſt reaſon is grounded vppon the number of the beaſtes name, expreſſed by the holy Ghoſte in the ſame propheſy, by the Greeke letters. χ, ξ, ζ. In which letters although there lyeth greate dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and difficulty to be vnderſtoode, yet the ſame is by certayne auncient Fathers expounded coniecturally to contayne the name of the beaſte. Of the which reade that which is alreadye expreſſed in the expoſition going beefore vppon the Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prophecy">
               <head>Another propheſie out of Daniel. <hi>Chapter.</hi> 11. <hi>ver.</hi> 28.</head>
               <p>HE ſhall returne and fret againſt the holy couenant: ſo ſhall he doe, hee ſhal return and haue intelligence with them that forſake the holy couenaunt. And armes ſhall ſtande on his part, and they ſhall pollute the ſanctuarye of ſtrength, and ſhall take away the dayly ſacrifice, and they ſhall ſet vp the abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable
<pb facs="tcp:2186:94"/> deſolation. And ſuch as wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly breake the couenaunt, ſhall flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with him deceitfully: but the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that doe knowe their God, ſhall preuaile and proſper: And they that vnderſtand among the people, ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct many: yet they ſhall fall by ſword and by flame, by captiuity and by ſpoil many dayes.</p>
               <p>Nowe when they ſhall fall, they ſhal be holpen vvith a little helpe: but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhal cleaue vnto them fainedly. And ſome of them of vnderſtanding ſhall fall to bee tried, and to bee purged, and to make them white till the time be out: for there is a time appointed. And the kinge ſhall do vvhat him lyſt: hee ſhall exault him-ſelfe, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie himſelfe againſt all that is God, and ſhall ſpeake maruellous thinges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the God of Gods, and ſhal proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, till the wrath bee accompliſhed: for the determination is made. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall hee regarde the God of his Fathers, nor the deſires of Women, nor care for anye God: for hee ſhall magnifie himſelfe aboue all. But in
<pb facs="tcp:2186:95"/> his place ſhall hee honour the God Mauzzim, and the God, whome his fathers knewe not, ſhall hee honour with golde and with ſiluer, and with pretious ſtones, and with pleaſante thinges. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prophecy">
               <head>Verſes propheſiyng the comming of Antichriſt.</head>
               <q>
                  <l>Cum fuerint anni completi mille ducenti</l>
                  <l>Et decies ſeni, poſt partum virginis almae:</l>
                  <l>Tunc Antichriſtus naſcetur daemone plenus.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe Verſes are thus engliſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>A thouſand, two hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred &amp; ſixtie yeres,</l>
                  <l>from Chriſt his birth expired,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhall the monſter Antichriſte be borne,</l>
                  <l>with diuel ful inſpired.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2186:95"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
